<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Averroeana being a transcript of several letters from Averroes an Arabian philosopher at Corduba in Spain, to Metrodorus a young Grecian nobleman, student at Athens in the years 1149 and 1150 : also several letters from Pythagoras to the King of India, together with his reception at the Indian court, and an account of his discourse with the King, and his gymnosophists, and his rules and precepts : his account of the power and efficacy of numbers, and magical uses thereof : to which is prefixt, a Latin letter by Monsieur Grinau, one of the Messieurs du Port Royal in France, to the ingenius Monsieur Gramont, merchant at Amsterdam, concerning the subject of these papers, and how they came to his hands : the whole containing matters highly philosophical, physiological, Pythagorical and medicinal, the work having been long conceal'd is now put into English for the benefit of mankind, and the rectification of learned mistakes.</title>
            <title>Correspondence. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Averroës, 1126-1198.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1981</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12369322</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12369322</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60522</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60522)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 884:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Averroeana being a transcript of several letters from Averroes an Arabian philosopher at Corduba in Spain, to Metrodorus a young Grecian nobleman, student at Athens in the years 1149 and 1150 : also several letters from Pythagoras to the King of India, together with his reception at the Indian court, and an account of his discourse with the King, and his gymnosophists, and his rules and precepts : his account of the power and efficacy of numbers, and magical uses thereof : to which is prefixt, a Latin letter by Monsieur Grinau, one of the Messieurs du Port Royal in France, to the ingenius Monsieur Gramont, merchant at Amsterdam, concerning the subject of these papers, and how they came to his hands : the whole containing matters highly philosophical, physiological, Pythagorical and medicinal, the work having been long conceal'd is now put into English for the benefit of mankind, and the rectification of learned mistakes.</title>
                  <title>Correspondence. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Averroës, 1126-1198.</author>
                  <author>Pythagoras. Correspondence. English. Selections.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 162 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Title page on microfilm copy begins with: Being a transcript of several letters.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:1"/>
            <p>BEING A TRANSCRIPT Of Several LETTERS From <hi>AVERROES</hi> an <hi>Arabian</hi> Philoſopher at <hi>Corduba</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> to <hi>METRODOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> a Young <hi>Grecian</hi> Nobleman, Student at <hi>Athens,</hi> in the Years 1149, and 1150.</p>
            <p>ALSO Several Letters from <hi>Pythagoras</hi> to the King of <hi>India,</hi> together with his Reception at the <hi>Indian</hi> Court, and an Account of his Diſcourſe with the King, and his Gymnoſophiſts, and his Rules and Precepts<hi>:</hi> His Account of the Power and Efficacy of Numbers, and Magical Uſes thereof. To which is prefixt, a Latin Letter by Monſieur <hi>Grinau,</hi> one of the Meſſieurs <hi>du Port Royal</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Monſieur <hi>Gramont,</hi> Merchant at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> concerning the Subject of theſe Papers, and how they came to his Hands.</p>
            <p>The Whole containing Matters highly Philoſophical, Phyſiological, Pythagorical and Medicinal. The Work having been long Conceal'd, is now put into Engliſh for the Benefit of Mankind, and the Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Learned Miſtakes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Epiſtola Praefatoria ad Librum Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentem; Scripta a Domino</hi> Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau <hi>ex praefectis</hi> Portus Regii <hi>in</hi> Gallia, <hi>ad Ingenioſum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> Gramont, Amſtelodamae <hi>Mercatorem.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SAepe ſaepius (Digniſſime M. <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont)</hi> Occaſionem teſtandi me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am erga te Gratitudinem expeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi, quam tandem nactus, non potui non prehendere. Sub tuis enim auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis &amp; impenſis primo operam dedi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris, utpote ex Anguſta oriundus fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia. Et neceſſe eſt &amp; fas videtur inde aquas redire unde primitus exiebant. Hocce Opuſculum quale quale eſt inopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato (&amp; praeter ſpem) caſu in manus incidebat. Quod non citius mihi acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit quam Tibi committere deſtinavi. Noſti optime Mr. <hi>Le Petit,</hi> Amicum No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum puſillo licet corpore, magno Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentem
<pb facs="tcp:60522:3"/>
Ingenio, pluribus abhinc Annis in <hi>Andaluzia</hi> apud Cantabros Hoſpitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Iſte Vir, parvulus quidem, &amp; inter noſtrates facetiſſimus Congerro, copiam mihi fecit hujuſcemodi literarum. Eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am &amp; fidem dedit eas <hi>Averroeana</hi> manu, ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſta latinitate Conſcript<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fuiſſe, &amp; ex Librario ſuo apud <hi>Cordubam,</hi> Anno 1231. Milleſimo Vigenteſimo Trige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo primo inde traductas, &amp; in priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam cujuſdam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nobilis <hi>Andaluzenſis</hi> Bibliothecam repoſitas.</p>
            <p>Jam vero reddenda eſt ratio, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obrem ego haſce Literulas in manus tuas miſi, ingentis munificentiae impar ſane <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Novinte, Amiciſſime V. etiam vel a primis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unabulis literas ſitire, &amp; plus operae ſtudio Philoſophiae dediſſe quam caeteri opibus comparandis. Hae ſunt verae Divitiae quae nec animis ſatisfacere ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Corpus laedere poſſunt, quo enim plus potantur eo plus ſitiuntur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Averroem</hi> itidem in medium inducere huic veritati aſtipulantem poſſumus: In confeſſo eſt apud omnes qui vel primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus
<pb facs="tcp:60522:3"/>
labris Medicinam illibarunt, illum de hac arte optime meruiſſe; quippe qui regulas conſervandae ſanitati, ſanae ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni innixas tradidit, qui temperantiam, quaſi utram<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> paginam in hac re facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, omnibus propoſuit. Illum vero de Menſtruo hoc, de quo jam agitur, calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſuum adjeciſſe teſtantur libri ab ipſo conſcripti Medicorum filiis haud quaque ignoti; quorum quidem copia <hi>Arabice</hi> Manuſcriptorum, in Bibliotheca Collegii Medicorum <hi>Londini,</hi> unicui<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> petenti exhibetur. Non is fuit qui temere ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam ſuam de rebus tulit: Arcanorum utpote naturae ſcrutator ſagaciſſimus, inveſtigator inſignis: Quin &amp; Arabs cum fuit, (ſole equos ſuos non tam procul ab iſta regione jungente,) hoc quicquid eſt ſecreti, tantum negocii neotericis faceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens, illum latere non potuit. Nec in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium uti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> revocari poteſt, quin ſcripta noſtrae <hi>Pythagorae</hi> ipſi ad manum fuiſſe, vel ſaltem fando audiviſſe de ipſius effa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; quoniam per omnia ſecum uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> adeo ſentire videtur, ut interceſſiſſe ſibi cum illo vel per literas vel aliter arctiorem
<pb facs="tcp:60522:4"/>
conſuetudinem nemo dubitaret. <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>goram</hi> vero quod attinet, omnes conſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tientiore pronunciant ipſum fuiſſe virum antiquis moribus, ſincera fide, honorem nedum Exiſtimationem vulgi parum affectantem, bono humanis generi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicientem unice, ſine fuco, citra verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum lenocinium, ſine verbis proletariis auram popularem Captantibus, plane ſine fuco aut dol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> malo, prout rationi non abſonos putaverat, conceptus ſuos literis mandaſſe': Adeo ut proclive eſt credere illum promovendae ſanitati, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>columitati<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tam Corporis ac animae ſumme nitentem fuiſſe. Quid multis? tot tanta<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſcripſit, tantis a multis retro ſeculis ipſum extulerunt laudibus cuncti ſanioris mentis Literati ut nefas omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no fuerit exiſtimationem tanti viri cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum iri. Siquis autem Luxuriae patriocinari ſatagit, dum <hi>Pythagoram</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſanae mentis ac injuriae mortalibus illatae inſimulant, quod promovendae ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taeque tectae conſervandae ſanitati animae corporiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> coelitus afflatus omnibus Carnium uſus, interdixit, dixit, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum
<pb facs="tcp:60522:4"/>
perpendet velim quot ſtrages, quantum malorum Ilias nobis incubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, quot truculenta morborum Sympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata hiſce diebus Medicorum remediis illudentia, ferociter inſtantia nobis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruunt, niſi ab ingurgitatione omne ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Carnium: Unde Languores deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae, unde in nos impetum faciunt morbi Scorbutici, Aſthmatici, quibus impar eſt congreſſus naturae, niſi a crebro &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperato indulto ciborum uſu; adeo ut non poſſumus non dicere nec indicta cauſa, gulam plures occidiſſe quam gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium. Hae ſunt V. Amantiſſ. rationes qua propter haſce literulas tibi Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico. Primo ſtatim vultu videntur eſſe praeludia Tyronum, quando vero prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratis Animis imbibantur, tanto vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur celeberrimis Antiquorum Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophorum ſententiis convenire, quanto cenſentur ab hodierna Scholarum rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere diſciplina. Multa quidem moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur &amp; tamen nihil agimus, niſi Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>janum equum inducimus qui omnia evertit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60522:5"/>
Apage ergo Scholarum Rudimenta, Nugamenta. Quo enim plus eis incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus, eo minus ſapimus. Quin<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> apud Scholas &amp; ſeptem in Academia conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus Annos &amp; etiamnum deliberamus utrum Concluſionem Syllogiſmi parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus annumeremus. O <hi>Diſcipulorum dura</hi> Ilia, qui guſtant quae non poſſunt concoquere.</p>
            <p>Hic ſolummodo praefert nobis facem Natura, &amp; quo diligentius eam ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur eo propius veritati accedimus, Optima Scientiarum Magiſtra &amp; Dux Vitae.</p>
            <p>Non opus eſt <hi>Dom. Gra.</hi> pluribus verbis, quam ut has literas in teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um maximae erga te Gratitudinis acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias &amp; boni Conſules.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. Grinau.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dat. Non.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Apr.</hi> 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter Prefatory to the Enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe, by Monſieur</hi> Grinau, <hi>one of the Meſſieurs</hi> de Porte Royal <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>to the Ingenious Monſieur</hi> Gramont, <hi>Merchant at</hi> Amsterdam.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have often ſought for an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of Teſtifying my Gratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, which having at laſt found, I could not but lay hold on. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Influence, and your Expences, I firſt apply'd my ſelf to Study, deriving my own Birth indeed from a very mean Family. And it is neceſſary that Rivers ſhou'd return from whence they firſt flow'd.</p>
            <p>This little Treatiſe, ſuch as it is, very unexpectedly fell into my Hands, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately I determined to ſend it to you. You know our Friend <hi>M. L. Petit,</hi> a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though of a weak Body, yet of a very
<pb facs="tcp:60522:6"/>
ſtrong <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, who has for many Years ſince reſided in <hi>Andaluzia</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> that little Man, and pleaſant Companion, firſt gave me a Copy of theſe Letters, and alſo affirm'd that they were written by <hi>Averroes</hi> own Hand in Ancient Latin, and in the Year brought from his Study at <hi>Corduba,</hi> and laid up in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary of a certain Nobleman at <hi>Anda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luzia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I am to give an Account wherefore I preſent theſe Letters to you, an unequal Return of ſo large a Bounty. I know, Sir, that from your very Infancy you have Thirſted after Learning, and taken more Pains in the Study of Philoſophy than others in the Acquiring of Riches. This indeed is the true Riches, which can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cloy the Mind, or injure the Body; for the oftner they are taſted, the more they are deſired.</p>
            <p>We have <hi>Averroes</hi> himſelf confirming this Truth, who is acknowledged by all that have but the leaſt Reliſh of Phyſick, to have very well deſerved from that Art, he having laid down Excellent Rules,
<pb facs="tcp:60522:6"/>
built upon ſound Reaſon for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Health, encouraging, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending Temperance to all his Diſciples. And what his Opinion was concerning the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> of the Stomach, his Books, hardly unknown to the Learned, do abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly diſcover, whereof there is an Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Manuſcript Writ in <hi>Arabick,</hi> to be ſeen in the Library of the College of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians in <hi>London:</hi> For being a ſevere Searcher, and diligent Enquirer into the Secrets of Nature, he never raſhly paſt Judgment upon things: And being an <hi>Arabian,</hi> and having a nearer Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with <hi>Phoebus,</hi> whatſoever there is of Secret in this Buſineſs, that has crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo much trouble to our Modern Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, could not be unknown to him.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be ſuſpected, but the Writings of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> were in his Hands, and their Sentiments are ſo much alike, that none can doubt but that there was an Intercourſe and Correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Souls.</p>
            <p>As to what concerns <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind with one conſent agree that he was a
<pb facs="tcp:60522:7"/>
Perſon endued with Antient Morals, and Sincere Fidelity, affecting neither the Applauſe nor Eſtimation of the Vulgar, having only a particular regard to the Welfare of Mankind, not ſtuffing his Writings with Rhetorical Flights to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the Ignorant, always commending many wholeſom Rules, and uſeful Notions, to the Service of the World. So that it ſeems he was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bent to promote the Health and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare both of Body and Mind. What need is there to ſay more, ſo many Excellent Things have been Written by him, and with ſo many Praiſes have all the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in former Ages extolled him, that it would be highly unreaſonable to ſuſpect the Reputation of ſo great a Man.</p>
            <p>But if any one ſhall ſo far Patronize Vice and Luxury, as to charge <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> with Madneſs, for Interdicting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, and Killing, and Eating of Fleſh, let him conſider whence all theſe Slaughters, and Cruel Symptoms of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, paſſing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, even of Phyſicians, do proceed, except from an
<pb facs="tcp:60522:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntemperate Ingurgitation of all s;orts of Fleſh? Whence comes the Languor of Sloath, Scurvies, Aſthma's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Nature is hardly able to overcome, unleſs from a repeated Indulgence in the Eating of unwholeſome Food, ſo that we may truly affirm the Gullet to have deſtroy'd more than the Sword.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Reaſons, Sir, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd me to Communicate theſe Letters to you. At the firſt ſight indeed they ſeem to be the Exerciſes of Young Scholars, but when they are imbibed into prepared Minds, they will by ſo much the more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to accord with the Judgment of the Beſt Philoſophers, by how much they ſeem farther remov'd from the preſent Practice of the Schools; where indeed we endeavour many things, but do nothing, unleſs induce a <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe that overthrows every thing.</p>
            <p>Away then with theſe Trifling Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Schools; for the more we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to them, the leſs wiſe we grow. We ſpend Five Years at School, and Seven in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and yet are
<pb facs="tcp:60522:8"/>
in doubt, whether the Concluſion is to be reckoned part of a Syllogiſm. O the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Guts of Scholars that can endure to ſwallow what they can never digeſt.</p>
            <p>But Nature carries a Torch before us, and the more ſtrictly we follow her, the nearer approach we make to Truth; ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſt Miſtreſs of Arts, and Guide of Life.</p>
            <p>There's no need of more words, only I beg you'd pleaſe to accept this Addreſs in part, as a Teſtimony of the Gratitude of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> P. Grinau.</signed>
               <dateline>Dat. Non. <date>Apr. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:8"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Firſt Letter.</label>
BEing a Commendation of <hi>Averroes</hi> his Learning. A modeſt Requeſt to that Philoſopher to give a full Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction concerning the Nature of the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum</hi> of the Stomach.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Second Letter.</label>
That the Prejudices of Education ought to be ſubdued. That Philoſophy allows a greater Liberty for the Exerciſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than the Myſteries of Faith. The Vulgar Notion of the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and Diſapproved, and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Diſliking it aſſigned. The Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of the Common Opinion Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated
<pb facs="tcp:60522:9"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Nature of the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum.</hi> That Egg-ſhells and Oyſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhells are of the ſame V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tue in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>inal Operations with Powder of Peart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> often uſed by Apothecaries for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Purpoſes, and at the ſame Rates.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of. the Third Letter.</label>
Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Nature, Quality and Oper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> Deſcribed. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reſembl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the World. The principal ſeat of its generation. That a diſordered <hi>Menſtruum</hi> is an Argument of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed Conſtitution: And how the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order may be Remedied.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Fourth Letter.</label>
That Experience i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the trueſt Ground of Knowledge. The Reaſon why Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans commonly Miſtake in the Notion of the <hi>Menſtruum.</hi> The Office of the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum.</hi> Too much Nouriſhment preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the <hi>Menſtruum.</hi> The manner
<pb facs="tcp:60522:9"/>
of Concoction of Food in the Stomach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Benefits of the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> in Application to external Wounds and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The proper Means of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ting the <hi>Menſtruum;</hi> and what Meats and Drinks deſtroy it.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Fifth Letter.</label>
Whether there be any Fixed Salts in Vegetables or Animals, Determined Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tively; with the Reaſons aſſigned. Bitter Herbs afford moſt Salt. No Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Art can unfix Salt. The proper way of unfixing it. The Phyſical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of Fixed Salts. What ſort of Salt is moſt Medicinal. All Spirits drawn from Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, have the ſame, or very like Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. From what Vegetable the beſt is Extracted.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Sixth Letter.</label>
Methods to be Obſerved by Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive People. The Nature and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Milk diſcourſed of. The proper Seaſon of
<pb facs="tcp:60522:10"/>
the Year for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ating it. Methods to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by each Conſtitution.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Seventh Letter,</label>
The Excellency of Herbs, and how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. That Wind is an Epidemical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: The beſt way to prevent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Occaſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem. Of Faſting a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Phyſici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>Brachma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ter.</label>
Methods the <hi>Brachmans</hi> preſcribe to be obſerved by their Women, during the time of their Impregnation, Lying-in, giving Suck, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in reſpect both to Mind and Body. Silence Recommended. Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs Commended. The <hi>Brachmans</hi> Opinion of the Power of Muſick. Their Receipt to Cure Swelled Breaſts. Sugar a great Balſamick. Their manner of the Education of Youth. The great Influence
<pb facs="tcp:60522:10"/>
and Power of the three grand Spirits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e World. Idleneſs Condemned. The Reaſon why their Children never depart from the Law of their Fathers. An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce thereof produced.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Ninth Letter.</label>
The <hi>Brachmans</hi> Opinion of the Soul of Man. The Original of Man's Depravity. All Violence and Oppreſſion of Inferior Creatures forbid. Their Notion of the proportion of Rewards and Puniſhments in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he other Life, An Account of their Belief of Tranſmigration, and the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle State. The Power of Sympathetick Prayer.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Tenth Letter.</label>
The <hi>Indian</hi> King's Summons to <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> to appear at Court.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60522:11"/>
                  <label>Of the Eleventh Letter.</label>
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Anſwer to the King of <hi>India.</hi> Abſtinence from eating Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> proved as Ancient as the World. Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to inferior Creatures forbidden upon account of Moral Juſtice and Goodneſs. Hunting Condemned. The Dignity of the Animal Nature aſſerted and proved. How the Knowledge of Divine Magick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s attainable.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th Letter.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Account of the Powers, Vertues and Efficacy of Numbers: The Method of uſing them in the Cure of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</item>
                     <item>Of the Diſcourſe between <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and the King of <hi>India.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:60522:11"/>
Prejudice, Cuſtom, and common Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Enemies to Knowledge and Vertue. The Original Compoſition of Man. The Occaſions of his Degeneracy.</item>
                     <item>The true Reaſon of the Liberty of the Will aſſigned. That a Lawleſs Liberty to do what we will, is a miſtaken Notion of the Power of Man. Wherein the Dignity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd Power of Man does couſiſt. In what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ence Man is the Image of God, and how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ought to Govern Inferior Creatures. Power to do any thing is no Argument for the Lawfulneſs of doing it. The Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Brutes</hi> no Reaſon for our Abuſing them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Of the Thirteenth Letter.</label>
Of the Nature of true Religion. That it does not conſiſt in the Obſervation of external Ceremonies. Wherein it does conſiſt. That the Impoſition of needleſs Things in Religion, gives Birth to moſt of the Confuſions that happen in the World.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60522:12"/>
                  <label>Of the Fourteenth Letter.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>Of the Power, Excellencies and Effects of Muſick. The Subject of the Hymns and Songs of the <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their uſe of them annexed.</item>
                     <item>An Extract of <hi>Twenty Eight</hi> Precepts that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> left his Diſciples.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60522:12"/>
            <head>Metrodorus <hi>the</hi> Grecian <hi>to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verroes <hi>the</hi> Arabian, <hi>ſendeth Health.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Moſt Learned and Renowned</hi> Averroes,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving often read over thy Works, and conſidered with my ſelf the mighty Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy Learning, wherewith the whole Univerſe is filled; I am aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the unconceivable Activity of thy Wit, which in an imperial and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable manner extends it ſelf over all the works of Nature, ſearches into her moſt ſecret and abſtruſe Receſſes, and like an Univerſal Intelligence, ſeems a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to actuate the whole World of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. How much, and upon what accounts <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf ſtands Indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thee, thy very Detractors in ſpight of all their Envy are forced to acknowledge. And for what Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60522:13"/>
I in particular have received by Thy Writings, let this plain Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof be accounted by thee for a Teſtimony of my Gratitude, that I owe all the Reputation for Philoſophy that I have in theſe Parts, to the ſole Influence of thy Spirit and Genius. Thou ſeemeſt in all thy Diſcoveries to have ſome particular Inſpirations, and Nature appears to have ſingled thee out as a Subject whereon ſhe would be laviſh in the Bounty of her Favours. Thou art admitted to a particular Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and haſt been able to trace her through all her windings and turnings, and diſcerned her naked in her bare and ſimple form.</p>
            <p>Proceed therefore, moſt Noble <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verroes,</hi> to imitate that Heaven from whence thou haſt derived thy Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the further communication of the Rays thereof to Mankind. And ſince I have been honoured with ſome acquaintance of thy Thoughts, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to inſtruct me yet more fully in the Myſteries of Philoſophy. I find by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60522:13"/>
Writings of the Phyſicians and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers of theſe times, that they make the <hi>Menſtrum,</hi> as they call it, whereby both Appetite is provoked, and Food in the Stomach is digeſted, to be a certain Acid Juice or Humour in the Stomach, that by vertue of its Acidity or Acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious quality only, hath power to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and concoct the Food, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a Notion I could never digeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intreat therefore, thou wouldeſt ſend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy Opinion of this Operation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure in Writing by this Meſſenger, whom I have ordered to ſtay at <hi>Cordu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> till thy leiſure ſhall allow thee op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ortunity of doing it. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated</hi> Athens, <date>1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60522:14"/>
            <head>Averroes <hi>to</hi> Metrodorus.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Worthy</hi> Metrodorus,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Had been better pleaſed with your Letter, if you had been more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of your Complements: As to the Opinion the World hath of me, I take it in good part, though 'tis a thing I ſhall never endeavour after, always ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in chace a far Nobler and Richer Prize than publick Fame, even Truth it ſelf. This is the mark I aim at, and as oft as I hit the white here, I am as proud of the ſucceſs as he that has Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered a Kingdom. From my Youth my Studies bent that way, and the greateſt Difficulty I ever met with, was to ſubdue in me thoſe prejudices that I conceived from the Authority of common Conſent and Belief. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your diſlike of the Vulgar Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Menstrum</hi> well enough, only I could wiſh you had at the ſame time
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60522:14"/>
annexed your Reaſons, which ſince you have omitted, I will endeavour by what I ſhall ſuggeſt to confirm and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle your Judgment in that Point, and if I can poſſibly aſſign the true reaſon of what you enquire after. There are ſomethings unalterably to be believed upon the ſole Credit and Authority of their Tradition, withal being of ſuch a Nature as no humane Inquiſition can arrive at any further knowledge of. Such are the Myſteries of our Religion, concerning which we will endure no diſpute, our holy Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the prime Favourite of Heaven, having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Word for the Truth thereof. But in Philoſophy we are left to a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Latitude, like thoſe of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, whom they call wild; we are obliged to the Authority of no Perſon, but at Liberty to pick and chuſe, change and reſettle our Opinion as oft as our Reaſon directs; as a Ship that has the Port in view, ſhall notwithſtanding by reaſon of a contrary Wind be forced to tack and ſhift her Sails a great many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60522:15"/>
times before ſhe reach the Haven. Let us therefore, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> launch forth boldly into this part of the Sea of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and try what Diſcoveries we can make beyond the experience of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Adventurers. They indeed, as thou ſayeſt, affirm the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> to be an Acid Juice in the Stomach, which by Virtue of that quality only hath power of provoking Appetites, and procuring Digeſtion. How this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came to be generally embraced, I cannot tell, but to me there's nothing in Nature appears more monſtrous and ridiculous, for were it at all ſo, we ſhould in ſome manner or other be made ſenſible of it: For no ſooner is your Meat or Drink deſcended into the Stomach, but it muſt of neceſſity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate with this ſharp Liquor, whereby the whole would ſoon become ſharp too, which is indeed contrary to all experience; for if a Man Vomits an hour or two after he has Dined, what he brings up ſhall be ſweet on the taſte, and the quality very little altered, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60522:15"/>
what he has eaten and drank be of a ſoure Nature, or his Stomach de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd and corrupted by ſharp Juices. For if the Stomach did naturally gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſuch a Liquor, we ſhould una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably diſcover it when we were hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry by its flux and reflux in the Mouth; let this <hi>Menſtrum</hi> be of what nature it will, it muſt of neceſſity be abundantly increaſed by Faſting. Beſides, if it be of an acid or ſoure quality, how is it poſſible that our Food, which conſiſts of all natures and taſtes ſhould aſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it ſelf with this? What a Confuſion and <hi>Ataxy</hi> would be ſoon felt, to the utter prejudice of the Tone of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and digeſtive Faculty? The whole frame of Nature in the Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm would be diſordered, Acidity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an extream, will admit but of very few things to accord and agree with it. But this Conſideration, above all the reſt, doth more and more aſtoniſh me: Is it not prepoſterous to aſſign that for the cauſe of any thing, which of its own nature muſt neceſſarily work the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60522:16"/>
quite contrary Effect? It is agreed on all hands, That whenſoever ſharp and ſoure Juices lodge in the Stomach, they wound Nature in her digeſtive and attractive Faculties, contract and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Food, whereby it becomes more difficult of Separation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, generate Crudities, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Obſtruct the free Circulation of the Blood and Spirits; inducing a general Heavineſs and Indiſpoſition over the whole Body. Sharp Humours beget pricking Pains in the Breaſt, Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings in the Bowels, ſharpneſs of Urine, Fluxes, Gouts, and an infinite Train of Diſtempers. If the Complexion be Melancholick, Obſtructions and Opila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ariſe, from whence Head-achs proceed, and that Inimical Diſtemper called Vapours, for which there is no Remedy in Phyſick, the moſt available is Temperance and Order. If the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion be Cholerick they give Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Rheumatiſms, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> If Sanguine they cramp Nature in her very Radix by Convulſions, Conſumptions, Loſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60522:16"/>
of Appetite. If Phlegmatick they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get abundance of Crudities and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted Matter, which by certain paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is conveyed from the Stomach to the Lungs, and there becomes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſed into a white tough Subſtance that ſticks to the Wind-pipe: But when this ſlimy Matter is generated in great quantities, 'tis attended with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Coughs, ſhortneſs and difficulty in Breathing, and an unconceivable variety of Evils that make Life it ſelf uneaſie, by affecting the whole Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm with an univerſal Dyſcraſy. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I would fain know to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Phyſicians ſo frequently preſcribe Sweetning Medicines to their Patients. Is it not to abate ſharpneſs of Humours? Firſt in the Stomach; Secondly in the Blood, as Pearl, Egg-ſhells, Oyſter-ſhells, Crabs-eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which in Operation are much alike, <hi>viz.</hi> To rectifie the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and purifie the Blood. And our Apothecaries can tell you, that they often uſe Pouder of Oyſter-ſhells with as good ſucceſs as that of Pearl: I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60522:17"/>
for my part know no reaſon againſt it. Therefore, I ſay, if theſe and many other Medicines are given to temper and allay ſharp and acid Humours, muſt they not as oft as they are given have a very diſaſtrous Effect upon the <hi>Menſtrum?</hi> If that be, as they tell us, an acid Juice? Why then ſhould ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and acidity be an Enemy to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? For I do not ſee how there can be any natural quality in the Stomach, that is an Enemy to it ſelf; but Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth, that all extream quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are abominable to Nature in her ſimple and undepraved ſtate. From all which Conſiderations it appears, that the Liquor or <hi>Menſtrum</hi> of the Stomach, which Nature hath ordained for the Concoction and Separation of Meats and Drinks, can neither be ſharp nor ſoure, ſweet nor bitter, nor ſalt, nor aſtringent, nor of any manifeſt taſte or quality, ſo long as it remains intire and undebauched; and when any of the forementioned qualities are perceived, it is to be taken for granted, that the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60522:17"/>
Stomach is out of Tone, and entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſorder, as will more manifeſtly be apprehended, when we have taught what the true nature of this <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum</hi> is.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated</hi> Corduba, <date>1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Metrodorus,</head>
            <p>I Have already given my Reaſons for your diſlike of the common Notion of the <hi>Menſtrum,</hi> and having had a freer Communication with the Superiour Powers, ſince I wrote, whereby I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the whole Syſtem of Nature, as you call it, was revealed to me, I am unwilling to adventure the hazard of my Reputation, in acquainting you with my Thoughts on the preſent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. You know very well the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience we lye under on account of our Country men. 'Tis true ſome of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60522:18"/>
our Predeceſſors have been acquainted with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Hiſtory; and there are thoſe alive who think they have done Wonders, both in their Tranſlation and Remarks, and as I am informed, the Chriſtians make uſe of it to good purpoſe<hi>:</hi> But be that as it will, I am ſure I may aſſume a greater Liberty in Philoſophy, I am reſolved now not to be bound to the Cuſtom of the Schools, not to tye my ſelf up to Art and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, but barely attend the Inſpiration of our Prophet and his Angels in the Publication of that whereof I ſhall have the ſatisfaction, and thou the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fir.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Menſtrum</hi> or Liquor of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, hath the neareſt affinity and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of Dew. What Dew is to the Earth, the ſame is this to the Body of Man: There being as great a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this moiſt Vapour or <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum</hi> for the ſervice of the Body, as there is of Dew or Rain to impregnate and aſſiſt the Earth in the productions of her Fruits. And as the greater World
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60522:18"/>
influenced by the Wiſdom of its Divine Creator, and the Operation of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Celeſtial Bodies doth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to it ſelf a proper and ſuitable <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, viz.</hi> The Rains and Dews of Heaven, whereby the whole Syſtem of Nature is maintained and made fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; ſo it is with the Microcoſm or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle World: Man alſo hath a power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him by the friendly Courteſie of his Maker to Concoct and Separate the Food in the Stomach by unconceivably fitting it for the Nouriſhment of the whole Body; and as that Liquor or <hi>Menſtrum</hi> of the greater World, is of a mild, ſimple Nature, gentle in Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of no apparent and remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Taſte, as is evident from Water it ſelf, which if it were ſharp, ſoure, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or ſweet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could never be a <hi>Menſtrum</hi> ſuitable to the Nature of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, Fruits, Grains, Seeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereof there is a wonderful Variety, beyond the Limits of Humane Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick: And it is utterly impoſſible for a <hi>Menſtrum,</hi> wherein any Humour is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60522:19"/>
predominate, to aſſimulate it ſelf to ſuch a variety of Qualities. The very ſame is likewiſe to be underſtood of the leſſer World Man. So <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> you may perceive that in a ſound, healthy Conſtitution, the proper <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum</hi> is in its own Nature an Inſipid Liquor, abounding in quantity as the Health and Strength of the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abounds. The principal Seat of its Generation is in the Mouth and Glandulous parts of the Head, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes accordingly proportionable to the free and undiſturbed Circulations of the Blood and Spirits; thoſe whoſe paſſages are clear from Obſtructions, where the Blood and Spirits have a freer and quicker Motion, beget great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of it, and conſequently enjoy a ſharper Appetite, and better Digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are of ſound, healthy Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, free from Drought and Heat, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Brisk and Lively<hi>:</hi> On the other hand, if there be any manifeſt or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct quality diſcovered, forthwith the Stomach and whole Body is out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60522:19"/>
the Appetite becomes blunt and dull, Indiſpoſitions and Diſeaſes ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly follow: This is ſufficiently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in ſuch who live Temperately, that uſe to Faſt a proper time after they have eaten, till the Food be Concocted, this Liquor in them becomes plentiful, they can eat a good Meal without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring Drink, having ſufficiency of this Natural Moiſture to temper and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Food for ſeparation: But In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance certainly depraves the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and debauches the Appetite, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes the <hi>Menſtrum,</hi> and converts it into a tough Nature, or ſome or other of the forementioned qualities, which all are Infallible Indictions of a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and irregular Conſtitution. For it is a ſure Rule, where the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> is diſordered, the whole Body is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. You are to Note alſo, that every Man after due Faſting, hath the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt quantity of this Liquor, which as ſoon as he hath eaten doth much abate, the Food, as it were, ſoaking and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it up by the heat of the Attractive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60522:20"/>
Faculties, eſpecially if the Food be dry, ſalt or ſolid, it requires to be moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened and ſoftened by another, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Water hath the neareſt Affinity, as appears, in that it being drunk after any thing ſweet, ſoure and bitter, or of whatſoever extream quality, ſtill retains its ſimple and natural Taſte<hi>:</hi> And Experience tells us, thoſe who us'd themſelves to drink Water have the ſharpeſt Appetites, and beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion. Beſides, we daily ſee thoſe that have not this Liquor in ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, cannot eat ſo faſt, nor ſwallow ſo thick as thoſe that have, eſpecially if they eat Bread or dry Food (as I ſaid before) but are continually ſipping and drinking to drive it down: From all which we ſee it is of manifeſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to Nature to have a liberal Flux thereof from the Mouth to the Stomach, as being that which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally aſſiſts Nature in her other Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and carries along with it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Symptoms of the ſtate of the Body. Thus I have in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60522:20"/>
               <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> diſcovered to you your deſire, and ſhall continue to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it more fully in my next, when I come to Anſwer an Objection of our Adverſaries againſt us; Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated,</hi> Corduba, <date>1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Noble</hi> Metrodorus,</head>
            <p>WEre Friendſhip like that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Profeſſions; did it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a private and perſonal Advantage in all its undertakings; or did it at one view repreſent all the Difficulties a Man muſt engage in doing his Duty, I had either not wrote to you at all, or had deſiſted now. But to make uſe of the hazard of my Reputation, for a Teſtimony of my Affection, I ſhall proceed to enlarge a little further on the Subject in hand. As the beſt and trueſt Knowledge in the World is
<pb facs="tcp:60522:21"/>
founded upon Experience, if rightly underſtood, ſo the ſtrongeſt and moſt pernicious Errors are derived thence, if Imperfect Eſſays, and Accidental E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents are miſtaken for it. The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Adverſaries Opinion is laid on this, That generally when Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Vomit, (though never ſo ſoon) after eating or drinking, what they bring up ſeems to have a taſte and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of another quality than what they received; from whence they conclude, (and that raſhly enough) that the diſgorged Matter derives its taſte from the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> or Liquor in the Stomach which has infected it, and from that Conſideration infer a more irrational Conſequence, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> or Juice of the Stomach muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be of the ſame nature and quality that this Vomited Matter ſeems to be. This is a meer miſtake of Nature's Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. For be this voided Matter of what taſte ſoever, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>annot derive its quality from the proper <hi>Menſtrum;</hi> and if it be ill and unpleaſant, it can
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60522:21"/>
argue no more than that it proceeds from a corrupted Stomach. For the Stomach being before (by ill habits) depraved, and now by the acceſſion of unagreeable Food diſturbed, takes the opportunity to diſcharge it ſelf (as well as it can) of both its troubles at once, which is ſo far from giving us a true account of the <hi>Menſtrum,</hi> that it only argues a depravity in the Stomach, chiefly ariſing from an undue lying of the Food in the Veſſels for want of due Concoction and Conveyance, by which means all the ſweet and good qualities are drawn forth, and almoſt nothing out Excrement remains; for of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oever quality that be that you make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Meal of, if you Vomit ſtrait after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; what you deliver ſhall be ſweet, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etain the ſame taſte, or be very little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltered, unleſs there be a manifeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> it ſelf, of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Perſon can be ignorant.</p>
            <p>The Buſineſs of the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> (as we have ſaid before) is to ſupply the Mouth and Stomach with moiſture.
<pb facs="tcp:60522:22"/>
It being of a mild Nature, and gentle Operation, bows and applies it ſelf to all ſorts of Meats or Drinks that enter the Body, tempering and incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſelf with them, and by the power of its pleaſant moiſture, and the gentle heat of the Stomach, which (whatever ſome think) is no hotter than our Blood, melts and ſoftens the Maſs, whereby the attractive Powers and Faculties of Nature, from all the Parts and Members of the whole Body, Extract all the ſweet and wholeſome Vertues of the Food, every part draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch proportion of the Juice and Nutriment as is ſufficient to ſupply its wants; but if there be too much Food taken in, then the attractive Faculty is overcome by the Surplus, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Juices, and the Stomach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes dull, heavy and indiſpoſed. I am bold to ſay, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more injurious to the health of the Body than too much Nouriſhment, too Rich Foods and ſtrong Drinks; the moſt Simple are moſt Natural; the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60522:22"/>
great difficulty lyes in finding out the juſt meaſure and proportion in quantity and quality. Now when your Meats and Drinks come into the common Bag of the Stomach, as into a Lembeck, where they are all mixed, melted, and diſſolved, then the Operative Faculties of Nature ſeparate and divide them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to divers qualities. Firſt, into a Milky Chyle, whence the attractive Faculty draws forth the Vertue, and ſends it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Blood and Spirits. Secondly, in a Phlegmy Liquor, which is white, and conveyed to the Lungs, where it is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated again, and one part thereof congealed and hardned, having no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to void it ſelf, but only by the Windpipe. Thoſe whoſe Stomachs are foul, do not digeſt their Food to a requiſite degree, ſend groſs and flatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Juices up to the Lungs, begetting Obſtructions and Shortneſs of Breath. For this white Matter, or light frothy Subſtance, is by the natural heat of the Stomach, coagulated into various Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies, according to the power of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60522:23"/>
the Heat and Circulations of the Blood and Spirits. In ſuch in whom the heat is potent, and the Circulations free, thoſe groſs Juices are contracted into hard Lumps, and Nature ſends them up the Windpipe with eaſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and caſts them forth. But in Phlegmatick Complexions, whoſe heat is leſs, and the Circulations of the Blood and Spirits dull and obſtructed, this Matter becomes tough and glewy ſtops the Breaſt, is the Original of Coughs, ſhortneſs of Breath, ſoreneſs in the Stomach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Laſtly, another part into Excrement, which the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive Faculty drives downwards, and carries off in the Draught; and alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thinner Subſtances, which Nature ſtrains into the Ureters, and expels that way.</p>
            <p>The Uſes and Benefits of this Noble Liquor are many: without it we could neither chew nor ſwallow. Neither could the Attractive Powers of Nature perform their Operation in drawing forth the Vertues of the Food, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60522:23"/>
and ſcatter them into all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Parts, to the univerſal Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and Welfare of the whole Body. This is that they call an <hi>Euſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,</hi> a good Habit and Complexion of Body<hi>:</hi> when this <hi>Menſtrum</hi> performs all its Duties naturally and undiſturbedly, then there is a good ſtate of Health, the Complexion is freſh and gay, the Spirits brisk and lively; ſtrength and agility daily increaſes; in fine, the whole Microcoſm is in eaſe, health and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Nay, this <hi>Menſtrum</hi> in its pure and ſimple Nature does not only promote Digeſtion, and aſſiſt Nature in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Works, but alſo it reaches and extends it ſelf to the Cure of External Wounds and Sores. It is a Practice as Salutiferous as Ancient, to uſe faſting Spittle for Sore Eyes, and ſeveral ſorts of Swellings. This is often done with good ſucceſs, if the Method be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued; that is, if it be often applyed. For it is a conſtant and repeated Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that overcomes and cures. I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60522:24"/>
have known a Man, without any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Book-learning and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, that hath done Wonders in the Curing of Deafneſs, and Diſtempers in the Ears, to the Amazement of many Learned and Famous Phyſicians, by the ſole aid and vertue of faſting Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, with a quicker and more certain Effect than any Poultice or Plaiſter whatever: Dogs, and many Animals, have no other way to Cure moſt Wounds; and I my ſelf, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> have done the ſame: Which are all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Balſamick Vertue of this <hi>Menſtrum.</hi> Bread chewed in the Mouth aſſwages all Tumors and Inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if worked into a Poultice, and applyed ſeven or eight times a day, till the Cure be accompliſhed. So uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable is the Excellency of this Liquor, that if the Powerful Vertues of it were vulgarly known, your Common Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pericks and Chirurgeons would have but very little Practice. In many Caſes moſt People might be their own Doctor, and deliver themſelves from a great
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60522:24"/>
deal of Expence and Torment. We have in our former Letters ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the Generation of this Liquor. It is generated more or leſs in all parts of the Body, but eſpecially in the Mouth, and Glandulous Parts of the Head, augmented by the Heat and Motion of the Brain, and the quick and uninterrupted Circulation of the Blood. The more in quantity this <hi>Menſtrum</hi> ariſes, the ſounder and healthier is the Conſtitution, Reſpiration is freer and leſs troubled, and Digeſtion more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
            <p>The Proper and moſt Natural Means of the Generation of it, is Temperance, thin, fine Airs, all manner of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Exerciſe in the open Fields, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by Running Rivers, where the Air is more penetrating, and affords finer Spirits, that occaſion brisk and lively Circulations. This is evident from the Conſtitution of People accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to ſuch Exerciſes and Works, they have ſharper Appetites, better Digeſtions, generally exempted from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60522:25"/>
Drougth and Dryneſs in the Mouth, Obſtructions in the Stomach, <hi>Aſthma</hi>'s, and other Evil Conſequences of a Cloſe and Intemperate way of Living. Meats and Drinks that uſually promote and increaſe it, are thoſe of the moſt mild and ſimple Nature, ſuch as plain Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gruel, Conjieu-gruel made of Rice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Milk-pottage half Water, eaten from <hi>February</hi> to <hi>Auguſt;</hi> for after Cows are with Calf their Milk is tough and jellious. Bread, Butter, ſome Cheeſe, ſeveral ſorts of Herbs, Roots, Paſſets, Coco-nuts, Eggs, and other things of a temperate Nature. On the other ſide, all Salt Meats, ſtrong Drinks, Tobacco, and all other things that are unequal in their Parts, are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to conſume and dry up this Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Liquor. The frequent uſe of ſuch things beget Feavers and Scorbutick Diſeaſes, as do alſo all violent Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, too large Meals, and too long faſting. Theſe do mightily weaken the digeſtive and attractive Faculties of the Stomach, induce a torpid and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60522:25"/>
heavineſs over the Members. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs is alſo an Enemy to it, for thoſe that would have good Blood, fine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſtrong Limbs, and ſharp Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, muſt Labour even to Wearineſs, after which give Nature her due Reſt, and Temperance will perfect the work.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> I have at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved your Doubts in the Matter you deſired, and abſolved the Nature of the <hi>Menſtrum</hi> according to my beſt ability. I queſtion not but I have ſtirr'd up the Choler of ſome young Phyſicians of our time, but I matter it not, if I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you ſatisfaction, I have my ends; however, I have done my endeavour.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated,</hi> Corduba, <date>1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60522:26"/>
            <head>Averroes.</head>
            <p>IT is not poſſible for me, <hi>Averroes,</hi> to expreſs in words, the great and unaccountable ſatisfaction I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by your Letters, nor have you leſs honoured me by ſo Noble a Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence, than you have enlightned and improved my Underſtanding, by the Diſcovery you have made to me of Nature's Secret in the Buſineſs of the <hi>Menſtrum.</hi> Methinks the Sun does not with more radiant and powerful heat reflect its Rays from the lofty Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſides to the humble Valleys, than you have clearly from the height and univerſality of your Knowledge at once darted into my barren and uncultivated Soul, the more Illuſtrious Beams of Light and Truth: You were ever, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verroes,</hi> the Subject of my Wonder, but now the Object of my Emulation;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60522:26"/>
nay, it would almoſt ſtir my Envy to ſee the Poſſeſſion and Monopoly of ſo much Science in any Perſon's Hands but yours, who ſo well know how to uſe it, and ſo bountifully to diſpence it. And I beſeech you, let the Accompliſhments of my Deſires hitherto, be an Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to me of hoping to prevail with you to give my Curioſity ſome further Satisfaction in the Works of Nature, particularly in this, whether there be any fixt Salts in Vegetables or Animals, according to the common O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Philoſophers and Phyſicians, which ſhall be embraced by me with the higheſt Teſtimony of Reſpect and Honour.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Athens,</hi> 1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60522:27"/>
            <head>Metrodorus,</head>
            <p>IT is not the leaſt Delight I take, to ſee a Perſon of your Eminence and Quality ſo vehemently to aſpire and thirſt after Truth, beſides the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency I have to be able to contribute any thing towards your Noble Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. I greatly commend your Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which can never be unjuſt, while you have ſo ineſtimable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable a Prize in Chace, the Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof will more illuſtrate your Name, than all the Trophies and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of your Anceſtors. In anſwer then to the Queſtion you ſent me, I deny that the Sal-nitral Vertues of things can be fixed; for then there would be no waſte or decay: for you muſt know, that ſo ſoon as any Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, or other thing, arrives to its higheſt degree of Perfection, thoſe Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitral
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60522:27"/>
Vertues or Balſamick Spirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more or leſs Volatile, according to the Nature and Strength of that thing. Could you by any Art continue and maintain the Oily Vertue, or Sun's quality, in any Animal or Vegetable, ſo long would that thing remain in full ſtrength and vigour. All Death and Decay ariſing from the Evaporation of the fine Spirits and Volatile Salts. Take any Herb when 'tis in full force and vertue, dry it a little in the Sun, but not too much, then burn it into Aſhes, and from theſe Aſhes you may gather a great quantity of that Matter which the Phyſicians call fixed Salt. (A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Herbs, Wormwood affords the moſt by reaſon of its bitterneſs and heat.) But if you take the ſame Herb, and expoſe it to the Sun and Elements till it becomes light, dry, or like Chaff, till it hath loſt its ſmell and taſte, and then burn it, you ſhall find very little or none of that fixed Salt. There can be no ſuch thing as fixed Salt in any Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable, ſo long as it remains intire;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60522:28"/>
for if it were there, it were impoſſible for it to evaporate or fly away; but if you burn this Herb when it is in its full Vertue; the heat and violence of the Fire doth Coagulate or Condenſe the Volatile Spirits, and Oily Qualities into a fixed Salt, which Effect is to be aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the meer accidence of the Fire, and nothing elſe; even as the Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick or ſweet qualities in Spirituous Drinks, by a fierce Fermentation are turned and tranſmuted into a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Nature. By theſe little Arts Men can change one quality into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but for the moſt part for the worſe, <hi>viz.</hi> They can tranſmute the Noble Spirits and Vertues into a keen and ſoure quality, and thence into a fierce Sulphureous Spirit. And alſo in Vegetables, by the help of Fire capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and fix the fine and Volatile Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues into a ſharp ſtanding Salt, and neither the one nor the other can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to their former ſtate, but by the powerful Operations of the Heavens and Elements, which by their wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60522:28"/>
and undiſcerned Influence, can change and unfix that that was fixed, ſo that it becomes Volatile again, ſo great and admirable is the Power of God in Nature's Works. None of the Chymiſts Furnaces with their fierce and terrible Fire can unlock the Body of Salt ſo fixed; if you have any deſire to do that, you muſt hearken to the Voice of Nature, and attend her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Works in her own way. Take your fixed Salt, either of Herbs, Stones, Wood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſow or mix it with the common Earth (it will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly enrich the Soil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and enable it to produce a large and plentiful Crop) and by this means the Fixed will become Volatile again, and is the Life, Power and Vertue of all Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but in time it will again evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. There is no fixed Salt in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor made by Art, that this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod will not unlock and unmix, till it becomes a pure, fine, Volatile Spirit, but only the Crude, Unſeparate Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water-Salt, that we uſe with our Food,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60522:29"/>
which ſome affirm paſſes through us undigeſted.</p>
            <p>The Phyſical Uſes of theſe fixed Salts are much the ſame in Operation, as to quality, though they differ in ſtrength and power, according to the Vigour, Heat and Vertue, the Body from whence they are Extracted is endued with. All Salts i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Nature are quick, penetrating, and opening, and of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng duly compounded with proper Medicines. Of all ſorts of Salts, that of Tartar is the beſt and moſt Medicinal; for 'tis more ſubtle and penetrating than any derived from Herbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thoſe Phyſicians that have this by them, have no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſearch for other, let the Diſeaſe be what it will.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> I have over and above anſwered your Queſtion, both by proving that there can be no fixed Salts really in Animals or Vegetables: And have alſo given you the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and uſe of all fixed Salts Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted thence by Art. I had thought that by this time I had fulfilled your
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60522:29"/>
Requeſt. But another Queſtion, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting it ſelf, relating to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, I ſhall a little treſpaſs on the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſtolary Confinement, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to offer ſomewhat by way of Solu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to That, and ſo intirely diſmiſs the preſent Subject: Having already af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that there is very little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt fixed Salts, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a little further to acquaint you with ſomewhat of the Nature of Spirits drawn from Wine, Sugar, Fruits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Phyſical Operations.</p>
            <p>All Spirits, be they drawn from what they will, have, as to quality, one and the ſame Operation, only weaker or ſtronger, according to the Nature of the Matter from whence they are Extracted. Being taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, they have all, more or leſs; a hot-penetrating Vertue, and are of good uſe, if properly adminiſtred, <hi>viz.</hi> now and then as Medicines, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they become deſtructive to the natural Heat, and inimical to the Vital Powers; and after a <hi>Series</hi> of Paralytick Contractions of the Nerves and Sinews,
<pb facs="tcp:60522:30"/>
induce, as their utmoſt Malignity, Death it ſelf, which conſideration ought to have a peculiar place am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g thoſe who would make the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a ſhort Life, and not loſe the advantage of the moſt ineſtimable Bleſſings the Gods can beſtow, even Health it ſelf: When by Burning any Herbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Extract its Salt, which by no other Method can be obtained, do not you deſtroy, or at leaſt change and tranſmute, all the lively and brisk Volatile Vertues into another quality of a contrary Nature and Effect? The ſame is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all Vegetations when fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And hot ſtrong Spirits drawn from them, are much leſs Medicinal than fixed Salt, if not partaking of ſome neceſſary Qualification.</p>
            <p>Therefore as to thoſe forced Spirits of Scurvy graſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which make Men look like ſo many ſpotted Leopards, which the publick and ſcandalouſly Licenſed Quacks and Empericks, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their <hi>Orvietan,</hi> or diſguiſed Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrida<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Aqua S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iptica,</hi> of which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60522:30"/>
not one knows truly, even the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the Word, which deſtroys more than they pretend to Cure, are only to be regarded as ſo many Cheats put upon Mankind, and a meer Trick for an Impudent Blockhead to get a Penny at the Expence and Hazard of a Life better worth than his own. For I look upon all thoſe Cattle as the Peſt and Plague of a Nation, and ought to have the <hi>Libera nos</hi> fixed over their Door, if ever they deſerve to be Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of an Houſe.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> for fear I ſhould over-laſh, I will quit the Diſcourſe at preſent, and ſay ſomewhat more in my next; wherein ſetting aſide the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices of Education, the common Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Phyſicians in the Country, where I at preſent live, and the Vulgar Opinion of Philoſopers, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by following my Miſtreſs Nature, to contribute what I can to the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Curioſity of a Perſon, I believe ſo deſirous of being acquainted with Truth; Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated</hi> Corduba, <date>1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60522:31"/>
            <head>Averroes <hi>to</hi> Metrodorus.</head>
            <p>SInce my laſt I have met with ſome Occur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nces that I think may be of uſe to you in the Study you are enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in. I am ſufficiently acquainted with the Noble Diſpoſition of your Soul, which ſets too high a value upon Truth, to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> any thing paſs by you unexamined, and ſcorns to deſpiſe any thing, meerly becauſe 'tis eaſie to be had, and at a cheap rate. The true value of things is never leſſen'd by their being ordinary and common; for we are yet ignorant of the Nature of that which we moſt familiarly converſe with. How many are the Doubts the Philoſophers are perplexed with about the Subſtance and Operation of their Souls, even whilſt they are employing them? And how few, if any, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Conſtitution of their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60522:31"/>
Bodies, whilſt they daily carry them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with them, and ſeem to take ſo much unneceſſary care for them? Were we but better informed of our own Natures, it would conduce much more to the gratifying our Curioſity in the ſearch of Truth, and withal, deliver us from the power of many Accidents that ſo often ſurprize and overwhelm us. There would be leſs need of the Doctor, would every Man become his own Phyſician, which would very eaſily be done, could we but maintain a regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar obſervation of the condition and temperament of our Conſtitutions. Having therefore of late been particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly engaged to make ſome Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on a Conſumptive Perſon, I ſhall briefly communicate to you what Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods ought to be followed by People afflicted with that Diſeaſe, and that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally only, not entring into a Philo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſophical Diſquiſition of its Origine and Cauſe.</p>
            <p>To begin then, The loweſt and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt Foods, and ſmalleſt Drinks, are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60522:32"/>
moſt advantageous to ſuch as labour under waſting Diſtempers. All Spoon Meats made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Oat-meal and Water ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with Bread, but without Butter, are proper. Some commend Flower and Water eaten with B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead and Salt two or three times a Week, and Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colate made with Water, and only ſweetned with Sugar. Sometimes let your Food be mean, and other times rich, for Nature loves Variety; but then remember to eat ſparingly: Such People ought to be cautious of viſiting the Shades of <hi>Venus,</hi> which is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prejudicial, and is perhaps in many the Original of that Diſtemper. All ſorts of ſtrong Liquors are to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, alſo new Milk, though the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed do often adviſe it. Salt is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in moſt Foods, it ſtrengthens the Stomach, and procures Appetite. In fine, Temperance is the main thing to be obſerved, and it is ſafer to err in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity than quantity, which over-burdens Nature, ſtagnates the Blood and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and induces a general <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hexy</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60522:32"/>
through the whole Body. It is very wholeſom alſo to walk in the Fields, eſpecally by Running Rivers, where the Air is more fine and ſpirituous, and more readily penetrates the Body on all ſides, wonderfully helping the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Blood, and facilitating Digeſtion: Lying alone on Quilts and Flock Beds is beneficial for Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Perſons. Their Cloathing ought to be moderate, rather inclining to thinneſs, for heat gotten by Exerciſe is ſurely moſt ſalutiferous. Once a Day let them remember to drink a Pint of good Water, which will cleanſe the Veſſels of the Stomach, and help Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, the often changing their Cloaths will contribute much to a Cure, provided they take care not to catch Cold. This may be thought a ſtrange Method, but, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> I have ſeen the Power and Vertue of it by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: It abundantly refreſhes the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, enduing them with new Life and Strength, increaſes the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> of the Stomach, ſharpens the Appetite to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60522:33"/>
an high degree, and unconceivably aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts Nature in ſeveral reſpects.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I have touch'd a little upon Milk, I ſhall give my Opinion of it a little more fully. Milk in its own Nature is a noble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> healthy Food, but ſome better than other, according to the diſpoſition of the Cattle from whence 'tis drawn, and the Nature of the Paſturage whereon they feed; from whence ariſes that great variety in the ſeveral forts of Butter and Cheeſe.</p>
            <p>The principal Seaſon of the Year for the eating of Milk, is from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>April</hi> to the laſt of <hi>July.</hi> It is good indeed at all times of the Year, provided the Cows be new Milch; for it is by no means to be eaten after the Cows have taken Bull, for then it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thick, and as it were ſtagnated, difficult of Concoction, and exceedingly detrimental to waſting People, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally generates frothy and phlegmatick Juices in the Stomach, which is drawn and attracted by the Lungs; and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture having no other way to disburthen
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60522:33"/>
her ſelf of theſe Crudities, is neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſend the greateſt part up the Windpipe, occaſioning Aſthma's and Coughs, the foundation of inexplicable Diſeaſes, which diſcovers of what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance 'tis to be very wary in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of eating and drinking.</p>
            <p>I ſhall, before I finiſh this Letter, make ſome Obſervations that may be uſeful to ſeveral Conſtitutions, if duly regarded, and then take my leave of you till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion gives me liberty to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe further on this Subject. The Phlegmatick ought to eat when they break their faſt, Bread, Butter and Cheeſe, or ſome other dry Food, and not drink till two or three hours; of whatever you drink let it be of a middle ſtrength. This method will not only Purge by Urine, and open the paſſages, but beget a brisk Appetite for a Dinner. To eat a Toaſt and Oyl together, with a draught of good Ale and Beer, is very wholeſom; but if the Party inclines to fatneſs, then walking in the open Air is a good Remedy. It prevents Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60522:34"/>
and groſs Humours and unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably aſſiſts the Operation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The Sanguine Complexion ought chiefly to deſire the moſt natural, proper ſort of Diet, ſuch as ſimple Water-gruel, which by the innocent ſimplicity of its Compoſition tends directly to the quelling and moderating the extravagant motions of the Blood and Spirits, which ſoon reduce themſelves to their intended end, if not excited by the exorbitant power of Imagination. Variety and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in the Adminiſtration ought to be obſerv'd, for Nature is pleas'd not only with a variety of things, becauſe it is compounded of them, but becauſe 'tis conducive to Health. In the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'tis good to be ſparing; but after the fourth or fifth hour they may drink a Pint of an Exhilarating Liquor to their very great advantage. The Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick Complexion requires in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing half a Pint of good Water. (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) 'Twas the <hi>Theban</hi> Poet's Expreſſion, but never the leſs true; for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60522:34"/>
being his <hi>Horace</hi> ſays, <hi>Nulla manere diu nec vivere Carmina poſſunt Quae Scribun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aquae potoribus, &amp;c.</hi> However true it may be in Poetry, I am ſure 'tis falſe in Point of Health. Let ſuch feed on Water-gruel, or Pap made of Flower, and be cautious of drinking ſtrong Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, yet after Dinner they may drink a Pint of Wine, Beer or Cyder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Diſpoſition be Melancholick, let them take ſome exhilerating Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meats for a Breakfaſt dreſt up with But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Bread, Sugar and Salt. Their Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ought to be much of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the more they eat thereof, the more it will extend the Veſſels of the Stomach and Breaſt, and quicken the Spirits into a brisk and lively Motion, and withal diſpoſe them to a deſire of Mirth and Company, than which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be a more ready and eaſie Cure.</p>
            <p>Perſons of any of the aforeſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, muſt beware how they drink ſtrong Liquors in a Morning, which naturally in the beſt Complexions, create
<pb facs="tcp:60522:35"/>
and excite Fumes in the Brain, and an unremovable Dulneſs or Lethargy thro' the whole Body. For certainly Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meats accordingly prepared are in the Morning the propereſt Food, As well on account of their ſimplicity, which is more agreeable to Nature, as that they are moiſt, and moſt eaſily aſſimulate themſelves with the Craſis of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and paſs handſomly off in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if they are Aged People, they ought to eat that which is eaſie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction for the firſt part of the Day, and after three or four Hours ſuch eaſie Food as their Stomachs ſhall deſire, but withal ſparingly. And if they exceed, let them walk in the open Air, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves in ſome Exerciſe even to Laſſitude. This is evident from the Country People, who for the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enjoy a better ſtate of Health than thoſe who live always in Town, and if any of them miſcarry, 'tis to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to their Intemperance and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60522:35"/>
uſing the beſt and greateſt Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings beſtow'd on Mankind.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add this, that two Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Meals a Day is the beſt Method to preſerve or recover Health. And of Bread, that which is three or four Days old is better, and more Salutiferous than that which is newer, whether it be to recover a loſt Appetite, or ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then a decaying one.</p>
            <p>Thus much, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> I thought fit to Communicate to you at preſent, if any thing occurs worthy your Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, aſſure your ſelf I ſhall not be wanting one Poſt to gratifie your Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated,</hi> Corduba, <date>1149.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60522:36"/>
            <head>Averroes <hi>to</hi> Metrodorus.</head>
            <p>A Friend of mine being juſt upon the point of taking his Journey into <hi>Greece,</hi> I thought my ſelf obliged to lay hold of this opportunity of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating ſome few more of my Thoughts, and recommending a Perſon to you with whoſe Converſation I promiſe my ſelf you will be extreamly delighted; for a finer Underſtanding, a ſtronger Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a more bold and happy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, I think, are not to be found in any Man alive. But I ſhall ſay no more in his behalf, becauſe I would not foreſtall the Entertainment you are like to meet in his Society and Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>I have for ſeveral Days lived wholly upon Herbs, and find them exceeding healthful Food, and perhaps the moſt connatural and agreeable to the Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Humane Bodies of any thing in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60522:36"/>
the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. I would adviſe that they be always eaten raw, with Oyl, Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Salt, with Bread, Butter or Cheefe, for as much as they are of an hotter Nature then, and afford a finer and more delicate Nouriſhment, and generate leſs Wind, being far more cleanſing than when they are boyled. The boyling of them does, as it were, unlock the Aſtringent Band of Nature, ſo that the Liquor in which they are ſteeped, draws forth and exhales all the warm Sal-nitral Vertues, whereby the Herb becomes crude, and conſequently more purging, than raw. Cabbage and Coleworts, being boyl'd and eaten, do not only puff up and ſwell the Body, and increaſe windineſs in the Bowels, but alſo generate ill Blood, from whence dangerous Humours and Obſtructions do proceed. But if you take a light, hollow Cabbage, or tender Colewort, and eat freely of them, with Oyl, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, Salt and Bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you will find no ſuch Operation; the Effect will be gentle, your Stomach will be warm,
<pb facs="tcp:60522:37"/>
and free fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Wind o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>welling The like is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all ſorts of eatable Herbs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may be fed upon to the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> advantage of Nature.</p>
            <p>I have obſerved Wind to be almoſt an Epidermeal Diſtemper, eſpecially in Aged People: And the beſt way to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint and prevent it, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by eating all your ſolid Food, as Fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> quite cold, but Spoon-meats may be eaten as warm as the Blood, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what warmer: And I do aſſure you, the conſtant uſe of this method, will clear the Head and Stomach from Wind, beget finer Blood, brisker Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and cauſe a lively Circulation of all the Humours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cold is another Original of moſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, which proceeds generally from an irregular Intemperance in Diet, Exerciſe, or Coition; thence ariſe Fumes and Vapours into the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, Wind in the Stomach, Obſtructions and Opilations in the Breaſt and Lungs, which can no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be prevented than by obſerving
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60522:37"/>
a due and ſober moderation in Eating, Drinking and Exerciſing. And hence it is, that oftentimes, though there be no downright Sickneſs, yet Perſons find in themſelves a general Indiſpoſition, they have little or no Appetite, are hot and uneaſie. In ſuch caſes a gentle Purge or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be good; but a proper method in Meats and Drinks, will give Nature the beſt and quickeſt Relief, in regard Repletion, Intemperance, and an over-abounding Nouriſhment, are the Foundations of moſt Diſtempers. A due Faſting therefore is very benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial. Abſtinence is good at all times, but eſpecially in Sickneſs; for when Nature hath loſt her way, the motion of the Blood and Spirits are interrupted, the Stomach is foul, the Attractive, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtive and Retentive Faculties are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd of their Natural Power, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late diſorder'd, the Qualities in conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one with another, like Parties in an ill-govern'd State. What madneſs is it to force this miſerable Creature to ſwallow down the Inhumane Doctor's
<pb facs="tcp:60522:38"/>
naſty Pills, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>renches, Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Jul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, when the Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight abundantly better, with more Eaſe, and leſs Charge, be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually Accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſht. The <hi>Indian</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians did ſtrictly forbid this Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Practice<hi>:</hi> And the Wiſe <hi>Brachmans</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Bannians</hi> do in all ſuch caſes adviſe Faſting, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Patients to take very little, if any thing, beſides Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jieu, which is nothing but Water and Rice boiled together, which Liquor the Sick conſtantly drin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not of any ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Fruit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, and interdict the uſe of all ſorts of Spice, as permcious to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Stomach, by reaſon that they heat the Blood, and are hard of Digeſtion. But what ſhall we ſay? Theſe are ſo inveterate by Cuſtom, and ſtrengthened by Intereſt, that it is hardly to be expected that Reaſon ſhou'd convince the worſt part of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> you ſee the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of an old Man, who had at any time rather be thought Impertinent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60522:38"/>
than Ungrateful, which has been the only reaſon of venturing thus far on this Subie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. If the Gods give Life and Leiſure to write to you again, you ſhall have an Account of the Opinions and Preſcriptions of a certain ſort of People to whom a greater Reſpect is due than to my ſelf. It hath been my Folly to venture hitherto, who am look'd upon as an Infidel where I live, and am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone beholden to the favourable Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome Perſons (who have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted the little difficulties of Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and common Education, and by their own ſingle Vertue eſtabliſh'd to themſelves a <hi>Character</hi> above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Level) for all the Reputation I poſſeſs. For to deal plainly with you, my Friends have better Sentiments of me than I dare own, and ſuch as would make me bluſh, but that I have Learnt the difference betwixt Affection and Flattery. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated,</hi> Corduba, <date>1150.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60522:39"/>
            <head>Metrodorus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <p>HAving of late had ſome Reſpite from Buſineſs, I remembred my Promiſe to you, which I have at laſt performed. I have here ſent you an account of the Practice of the <hi>Indian Brachmans.</hi> They are a ſort of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, for whom I have ever had a great Eſteem, for as much as I have obſerved them very nearly to follow Nature in moſt of her Preſcriptions. A Method that I highly Approve, and ſhall therefore Recommend to you ſome Obſervations of theirs, perhaps not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy your Meditation.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, for the Method they uſe with their Women, during the time of their Impregnation, Lying in, and giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Suck.</p>
            <p>Their Firſt Precept is, That they be very Exact and Punctual as to the quantity and quality of their Food, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60522:39"/>
that they drink nothing but pure Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as it comes from the Spring.</p>
            <p>They command them to eat at ſet Meals, <hi>viz.</hi> about Eight in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Four in the Afternoon: For when the Worlds great Eye the Sun, that Centre of Heat, hath mounted the Meridian, they command all Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People to reſt and abſtain from eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking, eſpecially Women with Child. For that the Sun does forcibly open the paſſages of Nature, exhaling the Spirituous Vertues, from whence proceed Wind and Vapours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but about Four Afternoon they allow a greater Liberty for a full Meal, for the Evening being cool, they have a conſiderable time to digeſt their Food, the greateſt part of that time being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted for Reſt.</p>
            <p>They likewiſe adviſe a due Faſting, and at ſome times to abate in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and at others increaſe it again. Alſo to give Nature that which is moſt like her ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> variety of Foods, but this at ſeveral Meals, and not all at one
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60522:40"/>
time, ſeeing that the Humane Nature is allied to all things, and compounded of Variety.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, they affirm, That a due Abſtinence infinitely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to an healthy and happy Life. It fines the Spirits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cleanſeth the paſſages, frees the Circu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tions from groſs Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Obſtructions, confirms the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the Mind, rendring them fit for the Contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of Wiſdom and Vertue.</p>
            <p>They command their Women to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Exerciſe gently, Morning and Afternoon, in regard that it will contribute as much to their Off-ſprings Health as their own, and deliver them from the trouble of all Windy Diſeaſes and Vapours, with which many Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſo extreamly afflicted.</p>
            <p>They Recommend Silence to their Women, as a Noble Vertue: It makes the Mind ſedate, grave, and thinking, ſtrengthening all the Powers thereof, whereby they become more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and better able to endure the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60522:40"/>
they may meet with. For the Spirits of Women are naturally more Volatile than thoſe of Men; ſo that much Talking doth ſpend and waſt them, weaken the whole Conſtitution, and beget ſwelling, angry Humours, equally prejudicial to the Child, as to the Mother. For there is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Sympathy between them, upon which account the greater care is to be taken.</p>
            <p>They alſo commend Chearfulneſs, a Pleaſantneſs both of Mind and Manners, to their Women, for they affirm the Compoſition of the Elements in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are of a more fine and ſofter Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture than in Men, for which cauſe they are more ſubjected to Paſſions, apter to Love or Hate, and conſequently ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and more deeply wounded both in Mind and Body. Wherefore their Prieſts teach them ſeveral Divine and Moral Songs, Hymns of Praiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Believing that Muſick hath a certain ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret power of moderating and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Pathetick Motions of the Soul,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60522:41"/>
rendring the Mind more equal in their Operations.</p>
            <p>If any of their Women chance to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſwelled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſts or Tumors, they r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach them to make this following Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tice, which they eſteem to have an Univerſal Tendency and Effect. <hi>Viz.</hi> Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Rice and boil it in Water, and when it becomes thick and ſoft, they take a bitter Herb called <hi>(Tantaraboys)</hi> cut it ſmall, and mix it with the Rice, adding to a Quart of this Two Ounces of good Sugar, and apply it to the Sore Ten or Twelve times in Twenty-four Hours, which gives Eaſe the firſt time, and in a few Days heals the Diſtemper. They have a great Opinion of Sugar, taking it to be one of the greateſt Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſams in the World, if mixed with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Ingredients, and will often apply it alone to Cuts, Sores and Wounds.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Brachmans</hi> do adminiſter any Inward Medicines, they do it all by Numbers, affirming, That God hath made all things by Number, Weight and Meaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60522:41"/>
Thus you ſee, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> I have hinted a few Obſervations of the <hi>Brach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in reference to their Women, I ſhall only ſubjoin ſomewhat concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Method of Educating their Children, and ſo endeavour to bring this Letter to a Period.</p>
            <p>The firſt Thing they ſuggeſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate into their Children, after they can ſpeak, is, That God hath Endued Mankind with Three Demons or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that like Three Kings make War, and are in continual ſtrife who ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Dominion over the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which they properly call an Inward Warfare. The firſt Spirit is of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that Great Celeſtial Body called <hi>Saturn,</hi> from whence Originally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed Avarice, Calumny, Malice, Pride, Envy, Violence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But from the ſecond Spirit or Demon comes Love, Pity, Mercy, Compaſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo Temperance, Chaſtity, Sobriety and Philoſophy. And from the third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed mixed Thoughts, various and wanton Diſcourſes, Laughters and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60522:42"/>
and all that is called Phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</p>
            <p>They labour hard to make their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren underſtand the Nature and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of each of them, that they may be ſenſible which hath the reigning and predominant power in them.</p>
            <p>They call the ſecond Spirit the good Demon, and with great earneſtneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate to their Children, that they ſhould be Governed by its Dictates, and obſerve its Directions.</p>
            <p>They teach them, that it was from this good Angel that their Seers and Holy Men received the Law of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. They inform them, that it is a great Bleſſing, and a Token of being a particular Favourite of Heaven, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Violence and Oppreſſion, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards thoſe Inferiour Creatures that cannot defend or help themſelves. That the greater part of Mankind are govern'd by the Counſels of the other Demons, from whence proceed Wars, Murder, Deſtruction, and all manner of Miſchief.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60522:42"/>
From Three Years old to Seven they Inſtruct them in the Precepts of Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſetting before them the Excellence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertue, and the Reaſon of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Above all things, they commend to them a ſtrict and ſevere Juſtice, which they never depart from; for theſe Inſtructions are ſo early graffed in them, and ſo plainly repreſented to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em, that they become, as it were, incorporate, and grow up along with them, inſomuch that they are no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Moral Precepts, but have in them the force of Nature.</p>
            <p>They alſo very Vehemently and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically ſet before them the Uglineſs of an Idle Life. Nay, they ſay, Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is inconſiſtent with Life, for Life in the very Expreſſion implies Activity and Motion. They greatly commend to them moderate Labour and Exerciſe, and frequently put them upon the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the ſame, even in their very tender Age. They are very Exact in teaching them the Art of Numbring, and acquaint them with the Method
<pb facs="tcp:60522:43"/>
of God's Works <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Worlds; <hi>viz.</hi> The Heavens, Star<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Elements, the Amazing Varieties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, Vegetations and Minerals; how they were all made, and are wonderfully ſuſtained by the Invincible Power of the Omnipotent Creator. They teach them the Motions of the Celeſtial Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, their Courſes and Diſtances, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and Configurations, and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, they keep them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in what either Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys their Underſtanding, or Improves their Manners, always accuſtoming them to the Exerciſe of Patience, and the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rance of Hardſhip.</p>
            <p>Having therefore ſuch an Early Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and continually before their Eyes the Examples of their Parents and Aſſociates, the Notions of theſe Truths do, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it were, enter into their very Natures by repeated habits, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can remove them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Having been Inſtructed that every word in their Law proceeds from God, and at the ſame time, having imbibed a true Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60522:43"/>
of the Excellency and Juſtice of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing, they look upon it as his poſitive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommand, and dare not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey. Thus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Eſteem of their Law is planted in them, that no Avocations of Buſineſs, nay, nothing but invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Neceſſity can exempt them from a punctual compliance with the ſame.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here inſert one paſſage of their nice exactneſs to the Rules of their Law. It is held Sacred amongſt them to keep themſelves undefiled from any thing they think unclean, and if ſuch an Accident happen, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> compell'd to repair to a certain pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Purgation, where they are to undergo all the Diſcipline of that My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, before they muſt enter on their Buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſs. Some of that Religion, who were Factors, came to <hi>Surat</hi> to Buy up a Commodity to be Tranſported into <hi>Perſia.</hi> The <hi>Europeans</hi> having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof, and knowing the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe People lay under, one of their Merchants came near the Place where they ſat, and unawares took off
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60522:44"/>
one of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and touched them. Immediately <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> great<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Cry was heard, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves polluted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forced to leave their Buſineſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Place of Purgation, to the deſigned Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>European</hi> Merchant.</p>
            <p>If any of their Princes at any time deſire their Daughters for Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, they lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e their Longing, for they will ſubmit to the Severeſt Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures rather than break their Vow. They are never to be Engaged in the Armies of their Kings, for as much as they abominate all manner of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor can they ever be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with to become Servants, being extreamly Jealous of their Original Liberty. In all Revolutions of States they are free, and enjoy under all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments an undiſturbed Exerciſe of their Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on account of their Peaceable Deportment. They abhor all ſtrong Liquors, their moſt cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Drink is Water. They lye upon hard Quilts; oftentimes on the bare
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60522:44"/>
Ground. They neither Invade nor Covet any Man's Property, they are tenacious of the Cuſtoms of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, and remain ſecure in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of their own Vertue and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated,</hi> Corduba, <date>1150.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60522:45"/>
            <head>Metrodorus,</head>
            <p>THere is one thing more that will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me with Matter for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letter, and that is, Their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Tranſmigration of Souls, which ſhall be the laſt concerning theſe People that I ſhall trouble you with hoping that my over-forwardneſs in this matter, ſhall be underſtood as an Evidence of my Willingneſs to embrace any Occaſion of ſignifying the Reſpect I bear to a Perſon of your Character, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lover of Vertue.</p>
            <p>All our Philoſophers and Seers, both <hi>Indians</hi> and others, do firmly believe, That God hath made Man in his own Image or Likeneſs; which all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but few have ſo well conſidered it as they ought: And that Man does contain the Principles and Properties
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60522:45"/>
of all things Corporeal and Incorporeal; Alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is endued with an Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pable Body, which Body is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, enlivened or informed by an Et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rial Spirit, and ſo anſwers to the great Body of this World, from whence the ſame is taken, and therefore is an Abridgment or Epitomy thereof. And as he does contain all the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the groſs Elements, <hi>viz.</hi> Earth, Air and Water, <hi>that nouriſh and ſuſtain the Body;</hi> He has alſo the Principle of Fire and Light, that is, an Immortal Soul and Spirit, which gives Life and Motion to the Body of Fleſh, and anſwers to the Soul of the great World, or that mighty Spirit, which is the Moving and Vivifying, and moſt wonderfully Creative and Conſervative Power in this vaſt Syſtem of Things, which we call the World; and which does preſerve and maintain every part thereof in Beauty, Splendor and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. Now in this Illuſtrious Eſtate, Man was Created, and in him all Forms, Qualities and Powers, ſtood
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60522:46"/>
in equal Weight and Meaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if Man had continued in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then he would have imitated his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in all well-doing, and Governed all the Hoſt of Heaven in Love, and have been a Preſerver and Guide to all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Creatures, which would have powerfully attracted, not only the ſweet and benevolent Influences of Heaven, but alſo the Prayers and good Wiſhes of all the under-graduated Creatures, which was the ſtation he was made and ordained for, and to be a Co-worker with his Creator in all Friendlineſs, Love, Compaſſion, Mercy, and doing unto all, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch would be done unto: But Man departing with his Will and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, out and from this Glorious State of Unity and Concord, into all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary qualities, <hi>viz.</hi> into inequality, diſcord, fierceneſs and wrath, by which he forfeited the Grand Charter or Law of his Creator, and ſo quickly diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed himſelf of all the good Properties and Powers his Creator had endued him with, by which he is now become
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60522:46"/>
an Enemy, not only of himſelf, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reated Beings. He Curſes and Deſtroys all, and all Creature Curſe him, and the Evil Wiſhes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f theſe Creatures do not proceed fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m them cauſleſly, and therefore they ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often take effect, and powerfully draw down the Thunder-bolts of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on their guilty Heads<hi>:</hi> For that Great and Natural Law of Retaliation will have its Operation, and take place either in this World, or that which is to come, whatever ſome may vainly fancy to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Therefore they do Command all their Diſciples and Followers to forbear all Violence, Oppreſſion and Killing; for the Infinite Deity delights not in Man-ſlaughter; Strife, Wars and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, enter not into his Tabernacle: Our Creator does accept of the Practices of every one that does well, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates him in well-doing, for he is equal in all his Methods, and cauſeth the bleſſed and glorious Body, the Sun, to ſhine on the Juſt and Unjuſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60522:47"/>
the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtials to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon all. The Bleſſings of the Four Worlds are equally diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uted to all Creatures: Inferiours have a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> equal Privilege <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours he only preſerves and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtains the Univerſal Syſtem of Nature by the Hand of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>read Providence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in them lies to be like him. God will not Oppreſs nor Kill, therefore they will not: He gives Life, and does alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that Life; his Love a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are by his good Powers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this cauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will not ſtrike, hurry, hunt, oppreſs, kill, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> violate any of thoſe good Laws God has or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſervation of his Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, firmly believing, That if they do by their Practices of Life precipitate themſelves into Oppreſſion and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that they muſt undergo the ſevere Law of Retaliation, either in this Life, or that which is to come<hi>:</hi> If they do wrong, or unlawfully take any thing from their Neighbour, they are
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60522:47"/>
obliged: to return threefold, which is a full pardon for the Injury done<hi>:</hi> And the great Law of Nature is thereby ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and conſequently the Sin pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hunt, oppreſs or kill any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Creatures, what Satisfaction can we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in this World? Therefore th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> great Evils that cannot be: recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here, muſt of neceſſity be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, on the Soul and Spirit in the World to come, there to be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> according to the Merits of the Evil: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd therefore they believe that all that have unjuſtly Ruled in this World, ſhall certainly in the Life to come be puniſhed with a Beſtial or Servil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſtate and condition; and they that have polluted themſelves with the Blood of their own kind; their Souls ſhall enter violent, furious Men, of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable Diſpoſitions, that ſhall Live Miſerably, and Die by the Fury of War, and Humour of Princes: But ſuch as have by continual Violence Oppreſſed and Killed the Unrevengeful Animals, their Souls and Spirits ſhall
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60522:48"/>
be precipitated and revolved into the moſt Sava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Brutiſh Bodies. All ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Wrathful and Senſual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, do in the next World ariſe wild Beaſts, all according to the Nature of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> what qualities ſoever it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch a Body it attracts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cloaths i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf with. Therefore none in the Life to come ariſe Men, but only ſuch as have retained Humane Property, that have been Merciful, and done Juſtice unto all Creatures; ſuch paſs immediately into the Regions of Glory, and Sing the holy Songs of Peace; others who have Lived mixed Lives, compounded of good and evil, who have been Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to Man and Beaſt, and at other times they have committed Evils; and Oppreſſed God's Creatures, ſo that for the good which they have done, they enter into middle Regions, where they are purged from thoſe Evils they le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t unrepented of; in which time they make full Retaliation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Such Souls, the Prayers and good Wiſhes of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60522:48"/>
Men do mightily help and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and conſequently ſhorten the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Retaliation; For the Prayers of good and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> People, have power to break open all Principles, and whenſoever it find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſimile, it incorporates, and the good Powers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtrengthened thereby: For all God's Powers, both in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and External Worlds, are moved by Sympathy or Likeneſs; for Inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Diſcord cannot move Equality; therefore the good Wiſhes and Prayers of Obſtinate, Revengeful and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Men, do not avail the Deceaſed Soul, who is paſt into the middle Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions for Purgation, and who with great earneſtneſs preſſeth towards the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood; and therefore no Prayers nor Wiſhes can profit ſuch Souls, but only ſuch as proceed from Innocent, Juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en; for every Word, Wiſh and Prayer hath power only to penetrate into, and open the Gate of its own Fountain, that is, Evil Mens Wiſhes and Prayers penetrate and open the Fountain of Wrath, and ſtrengthen it:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60522:49"/>
and on the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rary, the good Wiſhes and Prayers of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Innocent Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> into Heaven, and all good, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whatever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> like it ſelf; for the Celeſtial Powers and Properties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Internal Nature, are not only moved, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by ſence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſon, as amongſt Men; no, but by Concord, Equality and Harmony: And for this cauſe we do ſo earneſtly, and with ſo great pains and diligence preſs our Children and Diſciples, to enter with their Wills and Deſires into Innocency and Well-doing, being confirmed in this great Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That Men cannot draw nigh, nor become one with the Fountain of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity, nor be heard of the Soveraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Being, but as we become like unto him, for every Like is moulded by its Likeneſs; Blood requires Blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Merciful ſhall obtain Mercy from the God of Peace and Compaſſions. For theſe and the like Reaſons we have (for many Generations) totally ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from all Violence, Oppreſſion
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60522:49"/>
and Killing, either of Men or Beaſts; for every thing, both in the good, and alſo in the evil, do as naturally, and as pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>lly, ſtir up and ſtrengthen its own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>perty, as the Loadſtone at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts Iron: We do likewiſe firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and it is one of our principal Points of Doctrine which we teach our Diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>les, <hi>viz.</hi> That if any Man do ſuffer his Will and Deſire to enter into the Practice of Vanity, Oppreſſion, Violence and Killing, both Men and Beaſts, be it under what pretence it will, ſuch do precipitate themſelves into the divided Powers of Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> into harſhneſs, fierceneſs, wrath and ſavage beſtiality, by which they loſe Humane Property, and grow hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, cruel and ſordid, having no Compaſſion, Fellow-feeling or Mercy. And if Men Die in this ſavage, brutiſh ſtate, they ſhall in the Internal World, when the Soul ſhall be reinveſted with a new Body, we ſay, ſuch polluted Souls will naturally attract ſuch Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of all things, as the Spirits are
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60522:50"/>
capable, and have a ſimile with. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the contrary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe that in their Lives have obſerved the Rules of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and refrained all Viole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Killing; Intemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ce and Diſcord, and who have introduced their Wills and Deſires into Innocency, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Compaſſion, and doing unto all Creatures as they would be done unto, all ſuch ſhall not only immediately paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into the Regions of Peace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but be cloathed with more perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beautiful, and more glorious, human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shapes and Forms. For 'tis not to be doubted, and our Antient Seers and Philoſophers do confirm, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, when the great and moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Creator moved himſelf, and had a deſire to manifeſt the hidden Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Internal Worlds, he cloathed all the vaſt numberleſs variety of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in each Climate and Countrey, with Corporeal Bodies, according to the Nature and Property of the Spirit; for each Spiritual Subſtance had power to attract out of all things ſuch Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60522:50"/>
Matter for a Covering or Body as had a ſimile with its own Nature, as appears moſt manifeſtly by the Shapes, Forms, Inclinations and Diſpoſitions of each Creature, and as the Internal Property and Diſpoſition of each Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did vary; and where the fierce Wrath did predominate, and had the Aſcendant in the Spirit, there ſprang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wild, ſavage Beaſts, and cruel na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed Birds of prey; but where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lities of the Internal Nature were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> equally mixed, there were fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more benign and friendly Creatures, as Beaſts and Birds more humane, tame and tractable, called clean Beaſts and Birds; alſo where the Spirit was more noble and equal, ſo the Bodies and Frames were accordingly: And as Man was in his Primitive Properties and Qualities, greater and more noble than any other of the Creatures viſible, ſo the great Creator gave him a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Body above all the reſt of the Lower Creation; for all departed Souls, who in their Lives keep the holy
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60522:51"/>
Laws of Humanity and Innocency have appeared to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> humane Forms and Shapes: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the good Daemons, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Powers, whenſoever they have had occaſion to cloath themſelves with Terreſtrial Bodies, they have appeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in humane Figures and Shapes, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>nſible Law of God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Nature, for every Spirit or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Power to cloath it ſelf with a Bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table to its own Nature, therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Seed as Men ſow in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Life, ſuch a Body they ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with in the Internal World, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they have introduced their Wills into Wrath, Fierceneſs, Oppreſſion and Violence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch a Body the Soul may greatly be expected to have in the other Life; the Truth of this, the whole Univerſe, and the numberleſs number of Creatures, both in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nimal, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable and Mineral Worlds do Teſtifie and Witneſs. Here, <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> you have a tedious, yet imperfect account of the Doctrine of the Metempſych<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſis,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60522:51"/>
firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; as they report; by <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath ſince been embraced by Men of Eminent Learning and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. It ſeems to be founded on the Notion of Natural Juſtice, the exacteſt Meaſure of Retaliation. I leave it to your better Judgment to determine the Point, but to me the Hypotheſis ſeems probable, till a more Certain and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation ſhall be pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with a better.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dated,</hi> Corduba, <date>1150.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:60522:52"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>King's Letter to</hi> Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>upon his Arrival into that Country.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Pythag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE have been informed by our Officers in the Provinces thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which thou haſt Travelled, that thou art a very Learned Man, which is a Qualification we have always eſteem'd and cheriſht. But it ſeems to us, that thou art not ſo Wiſe, as thou art repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be Learned, in that thou goeſt about ſpreading New Doctrines, and Superſtitious Obſervations, perſwading my People to forbear following the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of our Anceſtors, preaching up an Abſtinence from Fleſh. The Great Creator of all things, as he made the World for an Habitation for Men, ſo no doubt the Creatures are ſubjected to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60522:52"/>
their Dominion, and ordain'd for their Uſe and Convenience. Wherefore we Charge you upon Peril of our Royal Diſpleaſure, that upon ſight of this our Letter, you forthwith repair to our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace Royal, that we may hear what Thou haſt to alledge in behalf of thoſe New Opinions thou haſt vented in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parts of our Dominions.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:53"/>
            <head>Pythago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Firſt Letter to the</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndian <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Renowned King,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUR Religion recommends Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from Fleſh. Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie would in your Letter ſeem to blame me on that account, as if I had taught an unreaſonable Doctrine, and for this reaſon, that as God had given the World for an Inhabitance, ſo the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for Subſiſtence. I acknowledge not only your Slaves, but the Beaſts of your Territories are your own, and you may uſe them as you pleaſe. But as the Notion of Tyranny is unreaſonable, ſo the Practice is unfeiſable, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever puts it to the puſh, will quickly find the Effects; for all the Philoſophers in the World can never perſwade us that we are Slaves, nor all the Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick
<pb facs="tcp:60522:53"/>
in the World convince the Brutes that they are of another Opinion. The Gods have made your Majeſty a King, Soveraign of a Numerous People, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your care, to be Preſerved and Maintain'd, not to be Pillaged and Deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed. So it is with the Univerſe, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eatures are our Subjects, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Slaves. Nature hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a many ways to continue its <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> without being beholden to the Slaughter-houſe. However,</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more than what an Epiſtolary Latitude will allow me, and aſſign my Reaſons, and make the beſt of my way to your Court.</p>
            <p>What I have Preached (O King) in your Dominions is no Upſtart Opinion, nor Phantaſtick Humour, but what I am able to abide by, and make good. For the Antiquity of our Courſe of Life, and the Innocence of our Doctrine, may be prov'd of equal date with the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60522:54"/>
The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors teach, That <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt Man, was placed in a Garden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that Herbs and Fruit were his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. And all Philoſophers agree, that in the Golden Age the Eating of Fleſh was never tolerated. It was the Corruption of Mankind introduc'd the Vice: Tho' afterwards in the <hi>World's</hi> Degeneracy, the Precept happen'd to be not ſo inviolably obſerv'd; yet the beſt Spirits, and moſt virtuous Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, tied themſelves up to the ſtrictneſs of our Rules and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>It is alledged by your Teachers, That we oblige our Followers to the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of things frivolous and vain, as not to kill any kind of Vermin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for fear of being guilty of Murder: Whereas the reaſon of this Prohibition in its niceſt ſeverity, is only to take Men off from their Natural Fierceneſs and Barbarity, leſt by accuſtoming themſelves in Cruelty towards Beaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Inſects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ſhou'd in time fall foul on one another. So that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Kindneſs is the Root of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60522:54"/>
and the ſafety of Mankind, the reaſon of our Precept.</p>
            <p>They alſo upbraid our Principles, in charging us with deſtroying that Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Royal Recreation of Hunting, which hath ever been accounted a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Exerciſe by all great Perſons in all Places, and in all Ages, and withal extraordinarily conducive to the Health of the Body, and improvement of the Mind in accuſtoming it to hardſhip, and the diſcipline of Vertue; but this is a miſtaken Allegation; for Nature needs not be beholden to Fury and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for its relief or ſupport. It is an Invaſion upon the Natural Rights of the Inhabitants of the four Worlds, and Men in the fierce purſuit of this Cruel Paſtime, are far more Ravenous than Dogs, Bears or Lions; for what thoſe rapacious Animals do, is only in order to ſupport their Lives, but more inhumane Men do it out of meer Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs. Though the Creatures are Dumb, and cannot addreſs their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor after the manner of Men, with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60522:55"/>
Hearts, and lying Tongues, yet there are powerful Complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ane Injuſtice, ſent up by them in a natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al way, which at one time or other will be heard to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of their Unmerciful Tyrants, We are miſtaken if we ſuppoſe it no Crime to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tcher and Abuſe theſe Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our Creatures, as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey were not parts of the Almighty Workmanſhip, and wholly exempted from the ſenſe of Pain. Are they not compounded of the Sevenfold Nature? Or is any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Elements wanting in their Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Are they not the Sons of the Stars, and partake of their Influence? And have they not all kept God's Laws, and the true method of Nature, and according to their kind, faithfully adore and worſhip their Creator? They are innocent and harmleſs in all their ways, though 'tis true they are not endued with Immortal Souls, and therefore the ſame Service is not required from them as from Man, who is created in the compleat Image of his Maker, furniſhed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60522:55"/>
with Excellent Gifts, Divine and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, appointed to be a Prince and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over this Inferiour World. Your Prieſts likewiſe are very inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to underſtand how we arrive to the Knowledge of Philoſophical and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athetical Magick. The firſt ſtep to this great Work, is to turn our Eyes inward<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with a ſedate Mind, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on the Unity of Powers, Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties, out of which Man is compounded, or that his Soul and Body do contain the true Nature of Things, both Material and Immateri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: On the one hand, Wrath, Envy, Contention, Fierceneſs and Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and on the other, Love, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Clemency, Compaſſion, and whatever deſerves the Name of Vertue and Goodneſs. Theſe are the two Fountains of thoſe Powers whereby Mankind is acted. The firſt excites to Violence and Oppreſſion, the laſt to Innocence and Mercy; ſo that thoſe that would purchaſe any Honourable Reputation in the World, ought to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60522:56"/>
command their Wills and Deſires to enter into this benevolent Fountain: For be pleaſed to obſerve, Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Mind is free, and no ſooner has this Benign Power obtain'd the Aſcendant over the inward Enemies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Members, but forthwith the Eyes of our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are opened; and we have a true taſte of the Univerſal Harmony. Thus we our ſelves, after we had inbibed the Rays of this Light, beheld all the Good that is in Things, and by help of this Diſtinction, the Beauty of Infinite Love appear'd plainly to the Eyes of our Mind; and being thus Enlightned and Confirmed, Error vaniſhed, and Truth ſhone out in its Native and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal brightneſs.</p>
            <p>After we had for ſome time Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed in the Holy Sanctuary, where we ſaw and heard things unutterable, this Holy Light, and Diſtinguiſhing Power, rendered us capable of Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating the wonderful Power of God, the Method of his Providence, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60522:56"/>
Courſe of his Government, managed by the Active Spirit of Life.</p>
            <p>We alſo lifted our Eyes up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and conſider'd the daily Motions of the Celeſtial Bodies, the Sun, Moon, and the numberleſs Company of the Stars, their Riſing and Setting, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Courſes and Revolutions, and the Various, and yet Harmonical poſture of their Configurations: Likewiſe the great variety of Beaſts, Birds and Fiſh, together with the Vegetables of the Earth, how every Creature, both Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and Terreſtrial, do with ſedate ſilence conſtantly ſubmit to obſerve and obey the Laws of their great Creator. 'Tis Man only that hath violated all Goodneſs and Sobriety, and by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Evil Powers has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Laws and Privileges of all other Creatures as well as his own, enſlaving them in the higheſt Bondage; for which depravity there is no Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but a ſpeedy entring of the Mind into the Holy Principle and Divine Power. Theſe Conſiderations promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60522:57"/>
us to lay a Foundation of Innocence, Self-denial<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Temperance in our Hearts, being aſſured that the good is always drawn and united to the good; and on the other ſide, the bad does with the ſtricteſt deſire and intimacy join and incorporate it ſelf with the bad. So that whoſoever offers violence to any Creature, at the ſame time opens the Gates of Wrath, Fierceneſs and Revenge: And on the contrary, he that preſerves any Creature by his good Inclinations, ſets open the Doors of Love and Gratitude. No Man can be a true Governour and Preſerver of his own Rights and Privileges, nor of the Creatures, unleſs the Fountain of Mercy and Compaſſion hath got the Aſcendant over him. For the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is to keep God's Laws, and in all things to imitate the good; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever breaks the Laws of Nature by hurting the Innocent, is Irreligious, and a Tranſgreſſor in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60522:57"/>
Beſides, we account praying to the Deities the meaneſt part of Religion: It is but a kind of Lip-labour, and may for any thing we know be no more than Hypocriſie, having ſingly no Evidences of its ſincerity. 'Tis the Obſervation of their Laws that the Gods regard; and One Act of Temperance and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is of more avail with them than an Hundred Superſtitious Sacrifices, and unneceſſary, and uncommanded Penances. That Man approves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt agreeable to them, who carries moſt of their Image in his Life and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Obedience to their Laws, and Conformity to their Natures, is the faireſt Acknowledgment of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and the higheſt Act of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a Creature can pay to his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor and Creator. Whilſt we live under the Conduct of our good Genius, obſerving the Rules of Juſtice and Gentleneſs, we become truly Religious. 'Tis by this ſoft, ſweet, ſilent Voice that we open a way to the Center of Goodneſs. The Internal Powers have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60522:58"/>
Immaterial Ears, they neither he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nor accept of Lip-ſervice. What pleaſes them muſt proceed from an Univerſal Power of Virtue within, that doth aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milate with all that is good; for by the Eternal Law all things are endued with a natural and influential Vertue, which by a Sympathetical Inclination joins with its ſimile whenſoever it finds it. This is that that opens the great Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Benignity. 'Tis the Practice of Goodneſs that unites Mens Souls to God.</p>
            <p>Theſe, O King, are the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that mov'd us to prohibit Violence and Cruelty, to keep our Hands clean from the Blood of Animals, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to our Diſciples a Friendly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with all things, to repreſent to them the Deformity of Vice, and the Beauty of Vertue and Gentleneſs, being well aſſured by the Univerſal Voice of God, and his Law in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that an <hi>Hecatomb</hi> of Bulls cannot be ſo acceptable a Sacrifice to him as an unpolluted Mind, and a Will wholly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60522:58"/>
prepared to follow his Directions, and ſubmit to his Providence. 'Tis to a ſtrict and ſevere imitation of him that we ſolicite our Followers, who is not delighted with Cruelty, but is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with the practice of Juſtice, when Men have Learnt the Art of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to others, as they would be willing to have others do to them. For no Man was made to be a Tyrant; and an Epicure, to domineer at pleaſure upon his Fellow Creatures, who at all times, and in all reſpects anſwer the end of their Creation better than himſelf. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut being hurried by the Spirit of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance and Error, he is become the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſturber of Nature's Harmony, putting her whole Frame in Tumult and Combuſtion.</p>
            <p>If Men paſs out of the Body in this wrathful Diſpoſition, what Regions muſt they enter into, and what Bodies muſt they be cloathed with? And ſince by the ſecret Power of the Eternal Law, every Spirit or Soul does naturally at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſuch matter for a Body as is ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:60522:59"/>
to its ſelf: Thoſe that have lived in the Power and Operation of the Lion, Tyger and Dog, and ſo far brutified their Nature, as to reſemble thoſe Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, muſt they not expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to be cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch hideous Forms and Shapes? As on the contrary, the Virtuous and Compaſſionate ſhall be adorned with the Garments of Innocency and Light.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſtep to Vertue is to do no Hurt, the next is to do all the Good we can, even to the leaſt of God's Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. What Creature ſoever you ſhow kindneſs to, the ſame doth natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally call upon the Fountain of Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for a Bleſſing upon you; ſo on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> other hand, the Cries of Oppreſſed Innocence take the deepeſt Root, both in the Fountain of Love, and the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Wrath. The Good attracteth and praiſeth the Good; and the Evil the Evil. Every Thing and Principle delights in its like: This is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all Natural Things that proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Immaterial World, and is in all its Particulars, Forms, Figures,
<pb facs="tcp:60522:59"/>
Qualities and Operations: And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever does underſtand the outward, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant of the inward; for in the great depth they are both one. The underſtanding whereof is of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely greater moment than your Men of War, for they are Sons of Violence, which do naturally attract the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Evil out of all things, and the Curſe of all Creatures takes place in them. Therefore, O King, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to ſuffer any falſe Reports to Exaſperate your Royal Inclinations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, who have no deſign of ſtirring up Sedition to the Embroil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your State or Kingdom, but only to communicate that Innocent and Benign Light Heaven has darted int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Souls, to as many of the Great Maker of the World's Creatures as we can perſwade to embrace it; that they may by peruſing the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of true Vertue and Philoſophy, become Dutiful and Peaceful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in their preſent State, and Bleſſed, and Happy Spirits in the future. As
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60522:60"/>
we doubt not, O King, ſhortly to make apparent, when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all have the Honour to be admitted into your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Preſence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60522:60"/>
            <head>Second Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Noble Prince,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOur deſire I ſhall anſwer ſo far as I may.</hi> The Vertues and Efficacy of Numbers are wonderful in their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, when aptly and properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, as the moſt Eminent Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers do unanimouſly confirm and teach. Now Number is nothing elſe but a repetition of Unity, for Unity doth moſt ſimply go through every Number, and is the common Meaſure, Foundation and Original of all Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and contains every Number join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together intirely, the beginner of every Multitude, always the ſame, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable.</p>
            <p>It is the higheſt Number in Muſical Harmony; where all Forms and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſtand in equal Weight and Meaſure,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60522:61"/>
and may juſtly be called Concord; therefore from Unity all things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, nothing was before it, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is after it, and all things that are, deſire the One, becauſe they all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the One God, Creator of an Creatures, which do endeavour to return to that One Fountain whence they proceeded. All Clemency, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Softneſs, Compaſſion, and doing unto all Creatures as we would be done unto, proceeds from the Unit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Concord, and is the Fountain from whence all true Knowledge and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ariſes; Unity and Harmony is the Preſerver of all Creatures; Light and Loye are the Off ſpring and Sons of Concord<hi>:</hi> All thoſe are moſt happy that obtain it, and all Creatures are moſt miſerable without it: Equality and Order are the Sinews and Health both of the Body and Mind, not only in this World, but in that which is to come. For this cauſe, Order, and the proper practice and uſe of Numbers, do migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily fortifie men againſt the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60522:61"/>
of evil Demons, and at the ſame time moſt powerfully attract the holy Powers and Communications of good Angels. For in what Creature ſoever the natural Qualities ſtand neareſt equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, or have made themſelves ſo by obſerving God's Law in Nature, they make that Creature moſt happy. He that Sins againſt God's Law, breaks and violates the Unity of his own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>By all the Philoſophical Mediums and Circumſtances in Religion, the firſt Founders intended to draw Men into ſome order, that they by degrees might through the Forms obtain the Unity. That thoſe People are moſt happy that taught their Followers to live an innocent, harmleſs Life, which bears the neareſt Relation to Unity and Concord: For we do affirm, That no inequality nor evil inclinations, can or do ariſe or proceed from the Soul or Mind of that Man, whoſe properties and inward qualities keep equal weight and meaſure. All Evil proceeds from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60522:62"/>
the many, that is from the inequality of the inward Powers of Mens Souls, therefore Harmony is the higheſt ſtate of the Soul, and the compleateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Senſes. Is not order the Original, which is nothing elſe but a compleat Number, the very Fountain whence all good Government proceeds, both in the Celeſtial and Terreſtrial Worlds? Let us conſider the Heavens, Stars and Elements, with their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and amazing variety of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wherewith the Four Lower Worlds are endued, more eſpecially the Celeſtial, where the holy and various Powers of good Demons are beyond all humane number, and all act and work in that exact Order and Number which the great firſt Being created them in; therefore all the Beaſts, Fiſhes and Fowls of Heaven are more innocent, and conſequently more happy than Men, becauſe they have kept their Law, and Unity, but Man has broken it in the higheſt degree. All Peace and Happineſs is comprehended within the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60522:62"/>
Limits of Equality and Concord; and on the other ſide, All Miſery and Evil is within the Bounds of Inequality and Diſcord, ſo that there is a neceſſity that every Man ſhould govern himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Order and Number, or ſome body for him; for ſuch as have not prudence to govern; and to give neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Orders for themſelves, ought to be governed by others; there being but few that have Minds that are able to govern themſelves, moſt being conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Rules of Cuſtom, be they better or worſe, therefore it is one of the greateſt Evils in the World, to be a Teacher and an Inventor of evil Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms; and on the other ſide, it is one of the greateſt Bleſſings to Teach and Invent innocent Cuſtoms, and good order of Living; for Man hath broken himſelf off from Unity and Order to that degree, that few incline to Vertue, except the greateſt number go before them, and that it become a Cuſtom to be Innocent and Vertuous: Therefore the <hi>Brachmans</hi> praiſe God, and his holy
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60522:63"/>
Powers, that they have not given the World any precedent of Violence, nor brought any evil Cuſtom; for Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in Cuſtoms rule over moſt Nations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Men are ſo highly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, that moſt of them will not only Kill others for not obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Cuſtoms, and believing in their Prophets; but they will die themſelves, rather than leave an evil Cuſtom to embrace a good one; ſo far are Mankind degenerated from Unity and Concord. For this cauſe we Teach our Followers to be careful, that they in their common Communications do not utter or ſpeak words that proceed from Fierceneſs and Wrath, nor to give themſelves Liberty to Complemental Jeſting or Flatteries, nor ſuffer the Tongue and the Heart to Rencounter each other; and for the better obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtinguiſhing from what Center and Quality all Words and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes proceed, they divide the Soul and Mind of Man into three Parts, Powers or Spirits, which ſome of our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60522:63"/>
Philoſophers call Qualities or Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they being the Grounds or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, whence all Imaginations, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, Words and Works do ariſe and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eed, <hi>viz.</hi> The firſt Power in Man's Soul is fierce, ſevere and wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and when this Power does obtain the Aſcendant, the Imaginations, Words and Works are harſh, bitter, ſurly, bold and fierce, filled with Envy and Malice, tending to Violence and Hurt; But when the ſecond Power go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns in the Center of the Soul, then the Imaginations, Words and Works are ſigned with the Character of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, with a Mild, Friendly, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Behaviour, filled with Mercy and Innocency, always tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Unity; But if the third Power or Quality have obtained the upper Region of the Soul and Heart, then the Imaginations, Words and Works are frivolous, frothy, mixed with wanton Jeſtings and Laughters, between Jeſt and Earneſt, always tending to evil. But oftentimes there is a mixture of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60522:64"/>
theſe Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lities or Powers, which run ſo high, that no Humane Number can penetrate into, or comprehend them, which is done by the help of Art and Reaſon, which do mightily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceive ſuch, to whom ſuch Diſcourſes are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, that do break the Unity, and make a great Tumult and Diſcord in the Soul. Upon which account we eſteem it unlawful to ſhew Anger to our Children; nor do we allow them to ſee vain phantaſtick Plays and Games; nor when Men, who are worſe than Dogs, that cauſe one fierce Beaſt to fight with another; neither do uſe them to Jeſt with or Jeer one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being well ſatisfied that in their green Years, every thing takes deep Root, that the Eſſences and Qualities thereof do never depart, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord being broken ſo early, it proves a work of great difficulty for ſuch, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to diſtinguiſh the Good from the Evil, or to obtain the Harmony of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or of their inward Powers: For let Men know for Truth, that the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60522:64"/>
Spirit or Power is given unto Man by his Creator, that Man might by its ſweet and friendly Influences, qualifie the Fierceneſs and Wrath of the firſt, and the phantaſtick Folly of the third, and ſo bring them all three into an equal Tone or Concord. We believe that the Knowledge, Power, Operation and Government of theſe three Spirits, and to be able to diſtinguiſh them, is of abſolute neceſſity; for if we do not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the nature of theſe Powers, we cannot have any true Knowledge, and where there is no Underſtanding, there is no Order, and where there is not Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, there cannot be any Concord or Unity. Therefore we do as much as in us lies advance Temperance and Order, and do prefer the uſe of Numbers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that God hath made all things according to Meaſure, Weight and Number; and the more we imitate him, the nearer we draw, and fitter we are to be joined to the uniform Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God in our ſelves: Therefore the <hi>Brachmans,</hi> when they prepare or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60522:65"/>
Phyſick, make uſe of certain Numbers and Words, according to the preſent Dictates of the Harmonical Powers of their Souls; always obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make uſe of the firſt Number that ariſes in the Soul, as being moſt ſimple, intire and free from the multiplicity of Thoughts, and ſtands neareſt unto Concord, which ſome of our Fathers call the <hi>Good Genius,</hi> or Good Spirit; but the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rabbies entitle it the Oracle, which being diligently waited upon, and its Dictates obſerved, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals in Mens Souls the great Myſteries of God, and makes known the Secrets of Nature, and all the degrees of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and Cleanneſs: It is this good Demon that teaches the proper uſe of Numbers, and all things neceſſary: For this cauſe when any that are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered deſire a Medicine, this good Spirit or Power is ready, and does im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately Dictate unto the Phyſician, what Methods, Herbs, Words or Numbers he ſhall obſerve and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. But for the moſt part we obſerve
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60522:65"/>
the Numbers and Method of Words following, <hi>viz.</hi> The Unity which in Medicine hath great Power and Vertue, when it ariſes intire and unmixed with the Imagination, or multitude of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Thoughts, then we are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our good Demon to ſome one ſimple Herb, and alſo how to prepare and apply it to the Sick Perſon, and when we gather it, we do turn our ſelves to the moſt glorious Eye of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and utter words to this purpoſe; <hi>O thou one only Power, Creator and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of all things, and who haſt endowed this Herb that I now gather with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſecret Vertue, bleſs the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe thereof to</hi> A. B. <hi>that he may by its ſweet Influences and thy Bleſſing be reſtored un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perfect Health of the Body and Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But note, that our Phyſicians or <hi>Brachmans</hi> do not keep nor obſerve a conſtant Method either of Numbers nor Words, they always vary according to the Dictates of the good Demon; for the Oracle of our Souls will always imitate God and Nature, whoſe varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60522:66"/>
is not to be comprehended by any humane Number; in which wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful variety conſiſts the higheſt degrees of unity; Therefore Man ſhould not put Locks on the Doors of his Spirit; for nothing hurts the holy Powers ſo much as to fix them in conſtant methods: For this cauſe Herbs and Medicines have not ſuch efficacy and power to Cure Diſeaſes and Infirmities, as ſome of the Philoſophers and Phyſicians talk of, they fixing certain Vertues in them; and ſo they adminiſter them, having no regard to the power of the Soul, nor to the preſent Dictates of the good Demon its Son, ſo that the Herb or Medicine is dead, and without Life and Spirit: But on the other ſide, when he that adminiſters obſerves the Voice and Dictates of the Spirit or Light of Mens Hearts, then the Medicine or Herb becomes full of Life, and hath a wonderful Operation, and Cures to an high degree. This is the method we and our Followers obſerve in the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſick, always following the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60522:66"/>
Directions of our good Demon, which leads us into as great variety, as there is of Creatures in the Animal, Vegetable and Mineral Kingdoms, or four Worlds: And though we Cure even to a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle with Sage or Balm, yet for the ſame or like Diſtemper we are led or direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome other Herb or Thing at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time by our good Angel; therefore we eſteem it a great Sin to obſerve cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain methods, and to kill Men by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Authority<hi>:</hi> No, all our Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power is from our Souls and good Angels, which Men ought to conſult in all difficulties. We do alſo make great uſe of the Number three, as being a holy Number, and a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Perfection, and moſt powerful, not only in Medicine, but alſo in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. We alſo prefer the Number Four, it being endued with great Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Vertue, being as it were the Foundation and Root of other Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as well of Artificial Things as Natural and Divine. The Number Five ſtands us in great ſtead in all our
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60522:67"/>
Magical Operations; this Number is as it were the Birth of the Son and Daughter of Light, and a Flame of Love, and is the wonderful Perfection and Virtue in all Operations; and ſome of our Fathers have entitled it the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Wedlock, and of Juſtice: This Number does contain many great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, which aptly uſed are of good ſucceſs.—The Number Six is alſo of great uſe, and is a Number of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in all the Magical and Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical Operations of Nature: Alſo the Number Seven has no leſs Vertue and Power than the other, and of which all our Fathers have made great obſervation in Sacred Things, in which Numbers all Myſteries are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. The Number Eight our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have made great uſe of, and they call it the Number of Juſtice and Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Note alſo, that the Number Nine is of great Vertue both in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines and Religion, and in all Magical Operations: There are alſo many other Numbers that are of great uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60522:67"/>
to all that live Innocent Lives, and obſerve God's Law in Nature; for Man is in Nature, and therefore he muſt work and penetrate into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Myſteries of God's Law, by the power of his Soul, and light thereof. This, O King, is ſome part of our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods in the Practice of Phyſick: We dare not in this place diſcourſe of our Secret and Divine Magick, nor of the wonderful things that are performed by the power of Sympathy and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy, the publiſhing thereof is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den us; but this is ſufficient to the wiſe, and he that underſtands how to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and apply theſe Rules and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods here ſet down, is not far from the great and moſt Secret Knowledge diſtinguiſhing the good Powers of God, the true underſtanding of which is the higheſt degree, both of Divine and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Magick.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:60522:68"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="extract">
                        <head>
                           <hi>An Extract of ſome of the Precepts and Rules that</hi> Pythagoras <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to his Diſciples and Followers.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>O Thou doubly compounded Man, fram'd of an Earthly Body, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced by an Immortal Soul, convert the Eye of thy Underſtanding inward, ſtudy thy ſelf, and thou ſhalt know the wonderful Powers and Qualities God has implanted in thee. Thou art the Similitude, the Reſemblance of all Powers, Worlds and Elements. In thee the true Natures and Properties of all Created Beings are contained. Thou art the Son and Off-ſpring of all Worlds, both Material and Immaterial, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou Vertually containeſt, and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolically repreſenteſt the Eſſences and Qualities of them all. For the Great
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60522:68"/>
Creator has indued every Being with an Influential Vertue and Vice, but more eſpecially thee, O Man<hi>:</hi> By which means there is a Secret and Sympathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Operation and Working of one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy on another. For which cauſe we Command and Recommend to our Diſciples and Children,</p>
                        <div n="1" type="rule">
                           <head>I.</head>
                           <p>Temperance, and an Abſtinence from all Hurtful Things in Eating, Drinking and Communication. That they keep themſelves Clean and Unpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted. Beſides, we have a particular regard to the great Law of Retaliation, to which man muſt ſubmit either in this or the other World. This is the Law of Juſtice, by which all muſt be tried, and none can be exempted: Which is the Original Ground and Reaſon of our Prohibition of Killing Living Creatures, and Eating Unclean Foods.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="rule">
                           <pb facs="tcp:60522:69"/>
                           <head>II.</head>
                           <p>The Gods are not only the Creators, but the Preſervers of all Creatures; and none can enter into the Regions of Bliſs, but ſuch as obſerve the Rules of Juſtice, and in all Things imitate them. For whoſoever oppoſes them muſt be compelled to undergo the Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Retaliation, ſeeing every thing is moved by a Sympathetick Motion and Inclination, and not according to Sence, as ſome vainly imagine, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Eternal Law in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and her ſecret Operation.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="rule">
                           <head>III.</head>
                           <p>The Heavens, Sun, Moon, Stars, and all the Elements diſtil their genuine Influences, and prolifick Vertues on all Creatures. The moſt inferior have an equal ſhare in the benefit of thoſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, Preſerving Powers according to the Capacity of their Nature. So
<pb facs="tcp:60522:69"/>
that to obtain their Favour, we muſt of neceſſity be like them in our Works and Communications.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="rule">
                           <head>IV.</head>
                           <p>We likewiſe forbid all manner of Violence and Murder, not only of thoſe of our own Kind and <hi>Species,</hi> but likewiſe of all inferior Animals. For no Man can do the Work of the Spightful Powers, but he muſt at the ſame time enter with his Will into their Qualities, which have an innate power to advance all kind of Cruelty, darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Soul, and rendring it apt and ready to receive and embrace the Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions and Impreſſions of evil De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, making it a Companion of all the Rapacious Beaſts of the Wilderneſs, which we call a double and treble, fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the heighth of Good to the fathomleſs Abyſs of Evil, cloathing the Soul with a Beſtial Body, the Eſſences whereof will ſtick to it in Eternity. For this Practice is contrary to the
<pb facs="tcp:60522:70"/>
Laws of Creation and Preſervation, 'tis Man only (by a whimſical Conceit) that makes the diſtinction, and not the holy Powers, for the Imaginary Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of himſelf, and the Maintenance of Society.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="rule">
                           <head>V.</head>
                           <p>Houſes and Hoſpitals, ſufficiently endowed, muſt be provided to preſerve the Inferior Animals from the Injury of the Elements in their Old Age. For Charity and Kindneſs to innocent and helpleſs Creatures, is the moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Service to the good Powers, attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the benevolent Influence of all things. The increaſing Dew of the Celeſtials ſhall never be wanting where Love abounds.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="6" type="rule">
                           <head>VI.</head>
                           <p>Whoſoever ſhall Reſcue or Buy any Beaſt, Bird, or other Creature, from the Hands of the Slayer, ſhall be bleſt
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60522:70"/>
in all he has, does, and be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker with the happy Communications of good Demons; for Charity where there is no Intereſt, and when the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it is chargeable, powerfully unites the Soul to all that is good and excellent, and is moſt agreeable to the Fountain of Goodneſs it ſelf.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="7" type="rule">
                           <head>VII.</head>
                           <p>Give Reſpect and Honour to all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Creatures, (becauſe they bear in their ſeveral Natures the Stamp and Impreſs of thy Maker's Wiſdom and Power as well as thy ſelf) eſpecially to the Cow and Ox, they deſerve it at thy hands, upon account of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceableneſs to thee. They are Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of great Value, and the holy Powers will not excuſe, if thou abuſe and torment them.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="8" type="rule">
                           <pb n="118" facs="tcp:60522:71"/>
                           <head>VIII.</head>
                           <p>Touch no Dead Body, for they are unclean; and if it ſo happen that any do, they ſhall be compelled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o undergo a Hundred Days Purification, and pay Ten Pieces of Money towards the Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Poor Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="9" type="rule">
                           <head>IX.</head>
                           <p>Drink not out of the Cup, nor Eat out of the Diſh of thoſe that Eat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Foods, or Drink ſtrong Drink; if any he found ſo to do, they ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a Hundred Days Purification, and pay Ten Pieces of Money for the uſes above-mentioned.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="10" type="rule">
                           <head>X.</head>
                           <p>No Strong Liquors, Wine, or the like, ſhall be drunk, only pure Water, which is the Mother of all Liquid Fountains, and moiſt Elements. For
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60522:71"/>
all Strong Drinks are injurious to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and deſtroy the Health both of Body and Mind.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="11" type="rule">
                           <head>XI.</head>
                           <p>If any Steal from, or Rob his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he ſhall reſtore Ten-fold, either in Goods, Money or Labour. And when any Perſon is Condemned in this manner, if any ſhall Jeer, Deride or Reproach him with his Crime, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo doing ſhall undergo the ſame Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, for Juſtice is the end of the Law.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="12" type="rule">
                           <head>XII.</head>
                           <p>Every Fifth Day in the Year ſhall be a Faſting Day, or a Day of Abſtinence, and the Maſter of each Family ſhall caſt up his Account of Expences, and what he has ſav'd ſhall be given into the Publick Stock for Charitable Uſes; for the Gods are much Delighted with clean and unpolluted Minds, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Souls.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="13" type="rule">
                           <pb n="120" facs="tcp:60522:72"/>
                           <head>XIII.</head>
                           <p>Let it be a Law, That all Ancient Men diſpoſe of their Eſtates to their Children, and Kinsfolks, and other good Uſes, reſerving only a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for their Maintenance; that as much as in them lies they may free their Minds from the Fatigues of this World, in order to be the more fit to Communicate with the Gods and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Powers,</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="14" type="rule">
                           <head>XIV.</head>
                           <p>Singing and Muſick ought to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, and is of great uſe, eſpecially at the time of going to Bed, for it natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally compoſeth the Animal Spirits, and prepares the Intellect for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of holy Demons; for all Compoſition and Concord is begotten by its <hi>ſimile.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="15" type="rule">
                           <pb n="121" facs="tcp:60522:72"/>
                           <head>XV.</head>
                           <p>No Man ſhall be the Husband of more than one Wife; for many Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men diſturb and diſcompoſe the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Unity of the Mind, and Strength of the Body, and is often the Source and Foundation of Enmity in Families and States.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="16" type="rule">
                           <head>XVI.</head>
                           <p>You ſhall be obliged to Pray to the Celeſtial Powers three times a Day, and after each Prayer Sing an Hymn of Thankſgiving to the Gods.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="17" type="rule">
                           <head>XVII.</head>
                           <p>If any have in their own Judgment offended in Eating or Drinking to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance; or in any other thing wherein their Conſciences accuſe them, though it does not fall under a publick Cenſure; They ſhall purge and cleanſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60522:73"/>
themſelves by Faſting and Prayer for one Day, which will contribute to the Reſettlement of the Mind and Strength of the Body.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="18" type="rule">
                           <head>XVIII.</head>
                           <p>You ſhall Eat and Drink twice a Day, at Nine in the Morning, and Four in the Afternoon, which will be ſufficient to ſupply the wants of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in that reſpect.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="19" type="rule">
                           <head>XIX.</head>
                           <p>No Woman ſhall Marry after ſhe hath been the Wife of one Husband, but remain a Widow, and ſubjected to a retired and ſedate Life, and eaſie Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. For Widows ſooner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come wanton than Maids, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more bold and forward. And by this means their Husbands Off-ſpring ſhall be better ſecured in their Rights, and the Deſcent or Diviſion of Eſtates more equally preſerved.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="20" type="rule">
                           <pb n="123" facs="tcp:60522:73"/>
                           <head>XX.</head>
                           <p>Every Son ſhall be bred up in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Trade, for as much as they eaſily learn what they daily ſee and practice in their tender Years. So that they will become not only more Curious in their Arts, but put their Parents to little or no extraordinary Charge, having learnt their Trade at the Age of Fourteen or Sixteen Years, which is uſually the time others are put out.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="21" type="rule">
                           <head>XXI.</head>
                           <p>Let Women accuſtom themſelves to a quiet, ſedate Life, eſpecially during the time of their Impregnation. Nothing is more hurtful to them than too much Talking and Paſſion. Let them live temperately, avoid ſharp and ſoure Foods, which will greatly conduce to the Health of themſelves, and the Child they are pregnant with.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="22" type="rule">
                           <pb n="124" facs="tcp:60522:74"/>
                           <head>XXII.</head>
                           <p>From Three Years of Age to Eight is the principal time for Teaching Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren all Science and Art, and all other things they are capable of handling. Then Impreſſions take the deepeſt Root, and the Mind then is leaſt prepoſſeſſed with Paſſion and Prejudice. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable to imagine what Children may do, if betimes they are rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted. I obſerve moſt loſe great part of their time for not being early inſtructed in true and proper Methods. For in this tender Age they are like Trees planted by the Hands of a Skilful Husbandman, in their due and proper Seaſon.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="23" type="rule">
                           <head>XXIII.</head>
                           <p>Let all the Food of Children be of a light and eaſie Concoction, for they afford both a dry and moiſt Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, fit for their Age.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="24" type="rule">
                           <pb n="125" facs="tcp:60522:74"/>
                           <head>XXIV.</head>
                           <p>If any Man Deſpiſe, Undervalue, Reproach or Backbite his Neighbour, or the Poor, he ſhall (if his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances allow it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) pay a Hundred Pieces of Money, and be Excommunicate for a Hundred Days: And when he hath made this Retaliation, the Holy <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> or Prieſt ſhall ſay unto him, The Gods and Celeſtial Powers diſpence the Influences of their Benefits to the Juſt and Unjuſt, to all equally according to their Pleaſure: And if Man wou'd ever be united to the Good, it is his Duty to imitate them. For there is no Mark or Character of the Favour of the Gods but this, which is the higheſt Number, and compleateſt Compoſition of the Soul.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="25" type="rule">
                           <head>XXV.</head>
                           <p>Let not Youth ſpeak in the preſence of the Elders, not having firſt ask'd
<pb facs="tcp:60522:75"/>
leave, for it is contrary to all Harmony and Order. And it ſhall be the Care of Parents not to ſuffer any unſeemly and undecent word to be ſpoken in the Ears of their Children.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="26" type="rule">
                           <head>XXVI.</head>
                           <p>All Differences ariſing between Man and Man ſhall be referred to the Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Three Perſons acquainted with the Matter, Two of whom ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe the Buſineſs, and if they cannot adjuſt the Controverſie, the Third ſhall have Power to do it, to whoſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence they ſhall, without Appeal, be obliged to ſubmit. And if any Paſſion ariſes, the Beginner of the Strife ſhall be Fined Ten Pieces of Money for the Uſe of the Poor.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="27" type="rule">
                           <head>XXVII.</head>
                           <p>In all Buying, Selling and Bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he that Sells ſhall pay to the ſame Uſe One Piece of Money for each Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,
<pb facs="tcp:60522:75"/>
and ſo in proportion, be the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain more or leſs.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="28" type="rule">
                           <head>XXVIII.</head>
                           <p>Seeing we have already commanded Temperance, it will be neceſſary only to ſubjoin, That you reſt from your Labour from Eleven a Clock till Two in the Afternoon. For the compoſing and ſettling the weary Faculties of the Soul, is a great prop and ſupport of the Health of the Body.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:60522:76"/>
            <head>Third Letter.</head>
            <p>AS to the Innovations, O King, concerning our Religion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are charged, I have theſe few things to return by way of Vindication, both of our Doctrine and Practice.</p>
            <p>Our Profeſſion is not to introduce new Principles, for Religion, I mean true Religion, is the ſame in all places, and at all times. The Ceremonies and external Rites thereof indeed are vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but theſe are as it were but Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Complements, which the Gods do very little, if at all, regard, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the ſubſtance, which is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in Thought and Deed, and an earneſt endeavour of being joined with, and an exact conformity to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Divine Light and Love. The Spirit of Wiſdom leads all her Children
<pb facs="tcp:60522:76"/>
in the Univerſal Temple, where there is no Controverſie nor Contention about Words and naked Forms; but there they all imitate their Creator, by doing good, and living innocently. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts chiefly in a Vertuous Courſe of Life, an exact and intire Obedience to God's Law; that is, that we labour to preſerve the Likeneſs of his Image in our Souls, in being Juſt, Temperate and Harmleſs. Nor is there any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty herein at all; for the Ways of God, and the Obſervations of his Laws are plain and eaſie, but the Humours and Inventions of Men are difficult and phantaſtical, very often pernicious both to Soul and Body: For when Men degenerate from the Light, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deluded by the power of a falſe Imagination, and vain Conceit of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to Aſſert their own Notions, and private and miſtaken Opinion of Things for Religion, violently impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them upon the Faith and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Mankind, as the Oracles of Truth and Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60522:77"/>
This has been the Source and Inlet to all the Controverſies and Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the World, and the Foundation of all the Miſery, War and Calamity that invades and domineers in every corner of the Earth. For when by treading in the Paths of Vertue, we keep cloſe to the Univerſal Law, we are in a direct way to be led to the true Mother of Peace and Unity, and then all Contention and Strife will ceaſe to have a Being in our Souls. It ought then to be our great Concern to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract our ſelves from the Senſuality of the Multitude, which is a very good ſtep towards true Religion and Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, living in a conſtant Imitation of our Creator, in being Innocent, Juſt and Holy: For 'tis not in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of External Rites, or Invented Ceremonies that Religion does conſiſt, but in an Univerſal Purity of Soul, in all reſpects conformable to the great Law of Juſtice, Love and Temperance, from which Eſtate Man is fallen, and Fierceneſs, Wrath and Inhumanity
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60522:77"/>
have aroſe in their place; and till this Principle be again renewed in the Soul, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here can be no true Religion acceptable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Univerſal Creator, and Firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is that we have preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Rules of Temperance, Meekneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Love to our Diſciples, that by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecting the Principle of Fierceneſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itterneſs in the Soul, they might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſimilated to the Divine Nature. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e could never perſwade our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at the Gods have any Pleaſure in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtruction of their Creatures; and do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieve that all Bloody Sacrifices are a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ench in their Noſtrils. How is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſſible to conceive the Fountain of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove and Goodneſs, to be delighted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith Cruelty? I have found in moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountries where I have Travell'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at the main Buſineſs of Religion is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uilt upon fine Shows, pompous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des, and a ridiculous Obſervation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>leſs and uncommanded Ceremonies; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is is meer Superſtition, and not Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on. Men have ſubmitted and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved
<pb facs="tcp:60522:78"/>
themſelves to common Practie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and chooſe rather to embrace a miſtak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and groundleſs Opinion for Religion than put themſelves to the trouble o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> finding out the Truth, which indee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the higheſt Enoblement of a Rationa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Soul. Cuſtom hides the Truth fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all Men in one degree or another; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 'tis no ſmall part of Self denial to ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come the Inveiglements thereof.</p>
            <p>So that theſe things conſidered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that impoſes Laws of Inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip on other Men, ought to begi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the Knowledge of God's Nature and himſelf, endeavouring to under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand both in a competent degree. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt diſtinctly and attentively conſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſtupendous and amazing Wonde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Work of Creation, and ſtrive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much as in him lies to conform his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions to thoſe, and imitate the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> perfect Example.</p>
            <p>Whoever therefore Worſhips God by the direction of Cuſtom and Opin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, is highly miſtaken; for by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> means he conſiders God rather as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:60522:78"/>
Inferior, as if he were obliged to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighted with ſuch manner of Service as he ſhall be pleas'd to allow him. Can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny thing import a more undutiful Contempt of the Divine Being? Shall we deface the Light of his Image in our Souls, to follow the Conduct and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of our own Extravagant Fancies. The moſt profuſe Sacrificer Honours not God at all, if he offers not with a Mind intentively devoted: For Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Victims of Irrational and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Things, are but Fuel to the Flames, and the prey of Sacriledge; but a Mind zealouſly fixed Eſpouſes the Divine Nature: For all like moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly tends to its like, and a Wiſe Man can only properly be ſaid to be a Prieſt, a Lover of God, and fit to pray; for he only can Worſhip who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds not the Qualities of what he is to Adore; but firſt making himſelf the Sacrifice, erects a Statue of God in his own Breaſt, and Builds in his Soul a Temple for the Reception of the Divine Light.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:60522:79"/>
Hence it follows, that he only is tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Religious, who having attained t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Knowledge of things Divine, returns h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own Perfections as the greateſt Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto the Cauſe from whence they flow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, wholly reſigning and devoting him ſelf to a deſire of Enjoying that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is altogether able to ſatisfie him.</p>
            <p>Thus much, O King, we though fit to Write to Thee concerning Religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, that thou mighteſt perceive th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Amendment of Mens Manners, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the leading them from the darkneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Superſtition and Error into the Light o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truth and Wiſdom, is the principa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scope and Deſign of our Doctrine, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not the Embroilment of Kingdoms and ſtirring up Sedition, as we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been unjuſtly repreſented.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:60522:79"/>
            <head>Fourth Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Renowned King,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ANother thing I find to be matter of Complaint againſt us, is our practice of Singing contrary to common Uſage and Cuſtom, nor do I know any grounds for Admiration, except that the Conſent and Joyfulneſs of our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings may create Wonder in our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors. We are perſwaded that the Soul of Man (when rightly tuned; that is, not miſguided by Paſſion, nor ſwayed by Intereſt) is a perfect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Harmony.</p>
            <p>Muſick is endued with wonderful Excellencies, and equal Parts, not only of the Celeſtials, but alſo of the Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrials: For numerous Sounds digeſted into pleaſant Songs, do wonderfully quicken the inward Faculties, and by a
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60522:80"/>
ſoft and natural Inclination, and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathetick Attraction, allure and unite all the Vertues and good Powers; and its influence is ſo great, when it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a well-tuned and compoſed Mind, that it does not only change the Affections, Intentions, Geſtures, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Actions and Diſpoſitions, but it impoſeth its own Harmonious Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, both on the Singers and the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. It pacifies the diſorder of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, not only of Men, but even affects Birds and Beaſts. Wild <hi>Indian</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants are tamed by Melodious Voices, yea, the Elements themſelves ſubmit to their power. Do not labouring Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſing to mitigate the Toil of their Employments; for Harmony chears and refreſhes the Animal Spirits, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an equal Operation of all the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, which in all reſpects forrifie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and at the ſame time chaſe away dull, ſordid Thoughts, and Saturnine Humours, rendring the Body and Mind capable to receive Divine Impreſſions. Muſick is a ſure and conſtant Friend to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60522:80"/>
Health, and many times we have known Diſeaſes give place to its ſaluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous ſtrains, by a Magical Power, and Sweet Violence, raiſing all that is good into equality, by moderating the Affections, and compoſing the Mind. Harmony is the true Muſick of the Spheres, acquainting Mankind with the Sympathetical Concord of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, that Golden Chain which unites Heaven and Earth. It is the true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of Man's Soul, fitting and preparing the Mind to underſtand both Divine and Humane Myſteries; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our Preſervation and Salvation in this World, and in that which is to come, do conſiſt in a Harmonious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Parts.</p>
            <p>Now our Songs are both Prayers and Praiſes to our Creator, for his Infinite Goodneſs and Mercy. Sleep is as it were a tranſitory Death, during the Body's natural repoſe, having ſhaken off for that time the Fetters of the groſs Senſes: And while the Spirits are upon the Wing, and as it were in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60522:81"/>
of Eternity, the holy Demons, or good Angels and Spirits, have their ſecret Intercourſes with our Souls, by whom, (as we are found worthy) they open and communicate the Divine Myſteries, to ſuch as have ſubmitted themſelves to the Government of the Innocent Harmonious Powers, (as I ſaid before.). Sleep is a tranſitory Death, in which ſtate there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion or paſſing of time perceived by our Senſes; and if we paſs away into Eternal Regions, we eſteem it a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and all our Fathers ſay, That an eaſie Death is a Favour from the Powers of Heaven, as being neareſt equality; therefore we ſing out our Prayers and Praiſes to our Creator, and as much as in us lies, do keep our ſelves ſenſible and mindful, that we may expect to be called out of this World every moment; alſo that our Dreams may be Equal and Harmonious; for Dreams and Viſions are the greateſt and cleareſt Arguments of the Immortality of our Souls, and the only way and means whereby our
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60522:81"/>
Creator does vouchſafe to reveal and communicate his Secrets to the Sons of Wiſdom. It is alſo to be noted, that our Songs being compoſed of equal Parts, and being impregnated by the Vertue and Power of our Minds, they do by a mutual Conſent and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, compoſe and unite all that is good, by a Sympathetical Inclination, which renders us capable of the holy Unity.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Reaſons, O King, that mov'd us to Recommend Muſick and Singing to our Diſciples, the good and innocent Effect whereof we have oftentimes and abundantly experienc'd.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:60522:82"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Account of a Perſonal Diſcourſe between</hi> Pythagoras <hi>the</hi> Indian <hi>King and his</hi> Gymnoſophiſts, <hi>aſſerting the Truth of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as found in an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Latin Manuſcript, atteſted by</hi> Averroes <hi>own Hand.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS ſoon as the King of <hi>India</hi> heard that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was come to Court, he ordered his high Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to provide convenient Lodgings for him and his Companions, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him a Day when he would give him Audience of what he had further to alledge in defence of thoſe Doctrines he had Preached in his Kingdoms, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly touching that Precept of his, forbidding to eat Fleſh, or uſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of Violence towards theſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60522:82"/>
innocent and harmleſs Creatures. The appointed Day being come, and the King ſeated on his Royal Throne, with many of his Courtiers and Gymnoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſts about him, <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to approach, and the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him after this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> we are aſſured, as well by thy Letters to us, as alſo by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of divers Perſons, that thou art a very Learned Man, we have therefore thought fit to ſend for thee to our Court that we might have ſome Perſonal Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with thee. We declare unto thee, that we do not approve of taking up things upon Truſt, and are utterly unwilling to encourage a Practice meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it has been cuſtomary. But to us it ſeems ſtrange that thou ſhouldſt teach our People abſolutely to abſtain from eating of Fleſh, and to forbear that Noble and Ancient Paſtime of Hunting, the firſt Exerciſe of Young Heroes, and that which fits them for the attempting all Warlike and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60522:83"/>
Actions, contributing as well to the Improvement of the Mind, as to the Strength and Agility of the Body, calling it a Cruel and Inhumane Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, altogether unbecoming the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Humane Nature. Let us then freely hear thy Reaſons; convince us, if thou canſt, <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and we our ſelves ſhall readily become thy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</p>
            <p>After which <hi>Pythagoras</hi> thus began his Diſcourſe; May it pleaſe your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, we have in our defence two po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Enemies to Encounter, Common Opinion, and Ancient Cuſtom. I am not at all inſenſible how difficult it is to prevail upon prejudiced Minds, and to perſwade Mankind from the Practice of thoſe things they have ever believ'd and uſed. But what we are now about to prove, is not Built upon the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of any Tradition, but is the reſult of pure Truth and Light darted upon the Underſtanding, by the Friendly Operation of the Creator's Spirit, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:60522:83"/>
upon the Souls of as many as have learnt to preſerve the Original Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in them, in obſerving the Dictates of God's Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Nature. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Man at firſt, was all Love and Sweetneſs; it was by the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Suggeſtion, and powerful Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Evil Demon, that Wrath, Contention, Fierceneſs and Cruelty ſet up their Throne in the World. For Man having eſtranged himſelf from the Fountain of Benignity, became a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Enemy to his Fellow-Creatures; and having by his evil Practices dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the Principle of Love, and defaced the Image of God, wherein he was at firſt Created, following the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of Evil Spirits, turned an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated Perſecutor of the innocent Inhabitants of the Lower World, wild in his Imaginations, and untractable in his Diſpoſitions. His great Creator had provided plentifully for him, without expoſing him to offend in ſuch a Rude and Barbarous manner. He appointed the Earth to him for an Habitation,
<pb facs="tcp:60522:84"/>
together with his Fellow Creatures; he ordained the Ground to bring forth Fruit, Herbs and Corn for their Food, and the gentle murmuring Rivers for their drink, the Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for their Beds, and the Thick ſpreading Trees to defend them from the ſcorching heat of the Sun<hi>:</hi> It is likely too he ordained the Beaſts of the Field for the Service of Man, ſo far as they might be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able without ſuffering Injuſtice, and being Cruelly dealt with. He was on every hand furniſhed with what might contribute to his Neceſſity or Delight, without being compelled to pollute his Hands in Blood, and worrying and tormenting harmleſs Creatures that bore God's Image, and the expreſs Signatures of Divine Wiſdom, as well as himſelf. It was for other Ends he was ſent into the World, <hi>viz.</hi> to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the Glories thereof; and in Reflection thereupon, to adore with an holy Heart and unpoluted Hands, the Immenſe Power, and Bountiful Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Creator. He was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:60522:84"/>
left at liberty, that his Actions might be Humane, not that he ſhould become a Lawleſs Tyrant, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable Deſtroyer. 'Tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the poor Brute Animals are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to their motions, they have the neceſſity of an unavoidable Law upon them, which they cannot tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, neither ſhall they receive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for the obſervation of it: 'Tis Man only whoſe Actions are capable of Reward and Puniſhment. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that he was ſent into the World with a Law written in his Heart to guide him in the paths of Vertue, Goodneſs and Innocency, that keeping up the Divine Life, he might preſerve the Image and Reſemblance of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and not degenerate to, ſo poor an Ambition, as of Exerciſing an Unjuſt and Tyrannical Barbarity over Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Animals, that continually acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged his Superiority over them by their Natural and Implanted Fear of him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:60522:85"/>
Then a certain Gymnoſophiſt of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> that ſtood by, ſaid, If things are as thou ſaiſt, <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> theſe Inferior Creatures are in a happier and more bleſſed Condition than Man himſelf: For what becomes of all his boaſted Authority? Where's the Dominion he pretends to hold by his Creator's Bounty, and the peculiar Excellence of his Nature, if theſe Creatures are exempted from his Juriſdiction, and not ſubjected to his Government? Thou haſt ſaid, that Man is the Image of God, and the Perfection of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Works in this Lower World; Where's the Preheminence then, if he has nothing to glory in, but the liberty of his Will, which had better a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times be confined, which at one time not only expoſes him to inexpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Perturbations here, but thereby Subjects him to his Soveraign's Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and to endleſs Torments here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; whilſt thoſe Creatures enjoy an undiſturbed ſecurity, free from the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:60522:85"/>
danger of ſuffering worſe in another place? The natural neceſſity of their Actions, makes all their motions eaſie, and delivers them from the fear of Tranſgreſſion and Puniſhment. Our Doctors have taught us, That as God is Soveraign Maſter of the Upper Worlds, and hath all Angels and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſubject to his Dominion; ſo, as an Image of himſelf, he has planted Man Lord in the Lower World, and endued him with Authority to command and controul all inferior Beings. That they were not Created as ſo many Pictures, only to gratifie the diverſion of his Eyes, but were alſo made for his Uſe and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in as many ways as he ſhall think fit to employ them; ſome to furniſh him with Food, ſome with Raiment, and others to ſerve him for Recreation and Diverſion. Nor in this does it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that any Violence is exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; for as much as having no Immortal Souls, and being but Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Beings, they have no Charter
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:60522:86"/>
to plead with Priviledge of Immunity from ſuch Services as the natural and peculiar ends of their Creation ſeem to deſign them for. For had the Great Creator, who is perfectly Good and Gracious, and cannot endure to ſee the meaneſt of his Creatures abuſed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended otherwiſe, he would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided means for their preſervation, furniſhed them with ability to avoid or reſiſt impending miſchief, or reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this exorbitant Appetite in Man, and have turned the ſtream of his Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations another way. For as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brication of all things was the Effect of his Power, ſo the particular manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and determination of all to their proper and reſpective ends, is guided by the conduct and concurrence of his Providence. And as his Wiſdom at firſt ordained theſe Creatures for ſuch and ſuch Ends, ſo his Spirit inſpires Mankind with Power, Sagacity, and Deſire to compel thoſe Creatures to the Accompliſhment of thoſe Ends for
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:60522:86"/>
which his Wiſdom had before contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and appointed them: So that Man is but the Maniſter of God in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in this reſpect at once purſues the end of his own Being, and that of other Beings too.</p>
            <p>After the Philoſopher had thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed, he retired a little, and the King ſtood up and ſaid, What ſaiſt thou, <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> to theſe Arguments, for to me they ſeem to have ſome Face of Reaſon in them. For if there be any Injury done to the Creatures in reducing them to our Service, and uſing them for our Paſtime, it muſt proceed, either becauſe they have a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Right of being exempted from our Power, or from ſome mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and Stipulation agreed to betwixt Man and them. If thou canſt make either of theſe out, we ſhall gladly quit the Cauſe, and ſubmit to thy Doctrine. For if thou proveſt the former, we muſt acknowledge our preſent Practice to be
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:60522:87"/>
an Invaſion; if the latter, Injuſtice: But if thou canſt prove them both, we ſhall readily confeſs it to be a Complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Tyranny, Cruelty, Oppreſſion and Abominable Iniquity.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Pythagoras</hi> advanced forward, and after having made ſubmiſſive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, anſwered; Moſt Mighty King, It is not only the greateſt Honour, but the moſt deſireable Happineſs and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, that I have the Liberty to defend the Doctrine I have taught my Diſciples before ſo Diſcerning and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacious a Prince, that is willing to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Cuſtom of many Ages, and the Practice of many Countries to an Unbyaſſed and Impartial Diſquiſition: This ſhall Illuſtrate thy Name more than the Trophies of thy Anceſtors, or the Succeſs of thy Indiſputable Courage and Bravery, that has Built ſo many Obelisqs to thy Fame through all the Territories of thy Enemies. Truth is the Brighteſt Gem in the Regal Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:60522:87"/>
and ſets it off with a far more ſhining Luſtre than all the Praiſes of Poets, or the extravagant and miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Commendations of Diſſembling and Hypocritical Paraſites. I ſee, O King, it is the Genius of thy Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thirſt after Truth and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and thou ſeemeſt to place a more than ordinary Felicity in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it. It is indeed a Noble Prize, and always Rewards its Adorers with laſting and ineſtimable Bleſſings. But the Miſery is, few poſſeſs it. I ſhall, I doubt not, before I have finiſhed my Diſcourſe, convince your Majeſty of the Truth of my Doctrine, as well in reference to thoſe two Points your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty has neatly comprized the whole Controverſie in: As in Anſwer to what that Grave Philoſopher has before been pleaſed learnedly to alledge. I ſhall firſt therefore, in humble Submiſſion to your Majeſty, begin with his Diſcourſe, becauſe it ſeems introductory to your Majeſty's Concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:60522:88"/>
He affirms our Doctrine to ſtate Brute Animals in a happier Condition than Man, and that it fullies the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Humane Nature in contracting its Dominion, and limiting the extent of its Power, as if the Excellency of Mankind conſiſted in a boundleſs Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of doing all the miſchief it can to Creatures that never did them any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and are unable to deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their Oppreſſion. Is this the Glory of Humane Nature to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Innocent, and overthrow the Weak? Is it the Pride of a River to overflow the Banks, and deſtroy the Neighbouring Countries with a violent Inundation? Do not all Men dread and oppoſe it, and endeavour to repair the Breach with all the skill and ſpeed they can? Do not they combine together to reduce the unruly Element to its proper bounds and limits? It is the Extravagance, not the Dignity of a Man, to commit Violence upon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is weaker than himſelf. He
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:60522:88"/>
ought to be look'd on as a Madman, he has violated his Reaſon, before he durſt injure one of the meaneſt of theſe inferior Creatures. It is a miſtaken Notion of Man's Power and Dominion, that puts him upon theſe Actions. All the Power he has, is to do good, and not evil; and if ever evil happen to be the Effect of that Power, it is an abuſe, and not the right uſe of it. When a Man reſtrains all thoſe Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Soul that prompt him on to unreaſonable Actions; when he bridles and curbs thoſe Appetites that ſolicite him to Intemperance; when he ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes that inordinate fear that Enſlaves the Soul, in ſubmitting it, through the Apprehenſion of ſome preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to commit a diſhonourable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Action, when he incourages thoſe Noble Seeds of Juſtice and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude that would lead him on to an intire Conqueſt over his Luſts, and diſtempered Affections; in ſhort, when he propoſes Vertue, Honeſty, and the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:60522:89"/>
ſatisfaction of a good Conſcience, as the end of his doings, then he evidences his Dominion, then he exerciſes his Power in a due and regular way. 'Tis this dignifies his Nature, and enobles him to a degree of Honour much above his Fellow-Creatures. But when he ſuffers himſelf to be hurried on with the impetuoſity of unruly Affections; when he permits Wrath, Fierceneſs and Cruelty to uſurp the Throne over Meekneſs, Patience and Humility; when Love, the Nobleſt and moſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing Power of the Soul, ſhall give place to Luſt, Chaſtity to Incontinence, and Sobriety to Madneſs, he is ſo far from being a Man, and exerciſing any juſt Authority, that he is utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man'd, and has debaſed himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the condition of any of thoſe Creatures he pretends ſo unjuſt a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over.</p>
            <p>Beſides, when we affirmed Man to be the Image of God, we never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:60522:89"/>
as that Philoſopher inſinuates, That God had ſet him up in Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of himſelf; and that as God is the God of Heaven, ſo Man ſhould be the God of this World: This is ſo wild a Notion, that it is inconſiſtent either with the Order of Things, or the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a dependent Being. It is an Impious and Sacrilegious Invaſion of the Creator's Royalty, and a Conceit of the Blackeſt and moſt Rebellious Tincture imaginable. Is not he the God of Heaven and Earth? Are not all the Beings in the Four Worlds, and in that Inviſible World too, the Work of his Hands? As they had their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Exiſtence from him, ſo they have their continual dependence on him. He holds his Soveraignty over them by a Right of Creation, whereby they owe to him a Natural and Indiſpenſible Subjection. And is Man any more God's Creature than any of the reſt? Are they not all their Maker's Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip as well as he? Do they not all
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:60522:90"/>
bear in them the undefaced and indeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Characters of a Divine Power and Wiſdom in a more unfullied and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted Purity than himſelf? Whence then can proceed his pretence of Right over them, who never offended their Creator, nor ſinned againſt the Law of their Being, as he hourly does? Let him exemplifie his Right of Claim to their Subjection and Obedience, if he would prove his Authority, or we ſhall never believe him. 'Tis in this reſpect only that Man is ſaid to be the Image of God, when his Will and Affections are conform to God's Laws, and when he makes thoſe the Meaſure of his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; when he lives in an uniform Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Imitation of his great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's Perfections, making his Univerſal Benignity, Love and Mercy his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Pattern. Not exerciſing an Uſurped Tyranny over Creatures more innocent than himſelf, vainly conceiting he has Right, becauſe he has Power to Oppreſs. It is indeed true, God has
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:60522:90"/>
endowed him with Faculties much tranſcending his Fellow-Creatures; he has given him a capacious Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a quick Imagination, a nice Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a retentive Memory, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacious Diſcernment of things; but then he expects from him a more ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and perfect Service, than from thoſe to whom he has aſſigned leſs Noble Qualifications. He has therefore fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him with a liberty of Will, which is the Foundation of Humane Action, that ſo his Vertues might in a more proper manner be ſaid to be his, not that he ſhould be left at liberty to do what he pleaſes, and thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not only an Enemy to himſelf, but to the whole Creation beſide. He was inſtructed with thoſe Noble Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in order to follow his Creator's Example in Goodneſs and Bounty, and not out of a ridiculous perſwaſion of his own Strength and Authority, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and fatally endeavour to imitate his Power and Soveraignty. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:60522:91"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his Scepter, his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and his Thunder; he will not have Man to meddle with any of theſe. 'Tis Goodneſs and Vertue alone that declare him to be the Image of God.</p>
            <p>As impertinent alſo is the Argument, That becauſe theſe things are in his Power to do, therefore they are lawful: For the lawfulneſs of any thing does not conſiſt in the eaſineſs and poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its being done, but in the Juſtice of doing it. It is unreaſonable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to argue, That the Governor of the World has given Man Authority to Kill, Torment, Deſtroy and Devour his Fellow-Creatures, becauſe it is in his Power ſo to do, otherwiſe he would have made better Proviſion for their Security. This is a grand miſtake, and an impious Arraignment of the Creator's Government and Care of his Creatures. For you are to know, O King, Man is here in a ſtate of Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Freedom of Will, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:60522:91"/>
Occaſions of exerting it are allowed him for a Trial both for himſelf and others, that he may perceive by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of acting Violence upon his Fellow-Creatures, how much he dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerates from the Example of his Maker, and that Original Purity wherein he was Created, that ſo by a timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon his Cruelty towards thoſe Inferior Beings, he may lift up his Eyes for Pardon to the Fountain of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity, and beg of him to renew that Principle of Compaſſion and Mercy in his Soul that was at firſt implanted in him. For aſſuredly, though theſe things at the preſent ſeem to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at, there ſhall be a Day of Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, when Juſtice ſhall be done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on uprepentant Mankind for their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity towards theſe poor Creatures, that ſend up inceſſant Groans and Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for Deliverance from the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Tyrant, Man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60522:92"/>
I had almoſt forgot one thing, and that is, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere he urges that there can be no Injuſtice, for as much as the Creatures, we are ſpeaking of, are but Temporary Beings, and not Immortal. If this Allegation has any force of an Argument, it muſt of neceſſity be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. For if they are but Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of this World only, it is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable we ſhould cut ſhort their Lives. If they are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of one Day's exiſtence, why ſhould we contract them to an hour. Is it not enough their Creator has determined their Being but for a little while, why ſhould we inhumanely diſturb it, or leſſen it? It is the Happineſs of Man, that when he falls here, he ſhall riſe again in another place, and if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haves himſelf according to the Dictates of the Law of God in Nature, in Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, Gentleneſs and Temperance, without the imputation of Revenge, Cruelty and Blood, he ſhall be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a more Bleſſed and Glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb facs="tcp:60522:92"/>
than 'tis poſſible for him here to enjoy.</p>
            <p>Neither can all the ſubtilty of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick in the World convince that theſe hard uſages we bring theſe under-gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duated Subjects to undergo, were ever appointed as the end of their Being by their Maker. Indeed in one ſence it is their end, <hi>viz.</hi> as it often happens that our Barbarous uſage of them puts a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to their Lives. In that reſpect we do but too often make an end of them; a woful end indeed. To deſtroy with delight that which God has made, to pull down with Violence what he with Wiſdom has Built up. This is making ſuch an end of Things, that if it be not timely repented of, will end in our own irremediable Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now, let blind, wretched, inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Man grow Proud and Plume him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this vain Conceit, that he is God's Miniſter to execute Violence and
<pb facs="tcp:60522:93"/>
Injuſtice upon Creatures more Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent than himſelf. Now let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aſt of his Imaginary Dominion over his Fellow-Creatures, who is a daily Slave to a numberleſs Train of Abominable and Deteſtable Vices, that hurry him about at pleaſure, and not ſuffer him to be Maſter of himſelf one Hour in a Month, nor perhaps one Month thro' the whole Courſe of his Life. Let him think it is ſufficient to exerciſe his Rage againſt his own kind, if there be a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for Cruelty, and not indulge the Impetuoſity of a Tranſported Paſſion againſt the Liberty and Lives of the Great Creator's leaſt Offending, and moſt Obedient Subjects. Then <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> held his Peace, and the King ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Satisfaction he received from his Diſcourſe, by ordering his Servants to take their Inſtructions from him for the Dreſſing his Food, that by beginning with himſelf, he might become a Royal Example of Reformation to all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects throughout his Dominions.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
